<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A nevve anatomie of vvhole man aswell of his body, as of his soule: declaring the condition and constitution of the same, in his first creation, corruption, regeneration, and glorification. Made by Iohn Woolton minister of the Gospell.</title>
            <author>Woolton, John, 1535?-1594.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1576</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15703</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25977</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120280</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855479</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855479</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20974</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15703)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20974)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 719:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A nevve anatomie of vvhole man aswell of his body, as of his soule: declaring the condition and constitution of the same, in his first creation, corruption, regeneration, and glorification. Made by Iohn Woolton minister of the Gospell.</title>
                  <author>Woolton, John, 1535?-1594.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 52 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Purfoote, dwelling in Paules Churchyard at the signe of the Lucrece,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1576.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20974:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20974:1"/>
            <p>¶ A NEVVE ANA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomie of vvhole man, aſwell of his body, as of <hi>his Soule: Declaring the condition</hi> and conſtitution of the ſame, <hi>in his firſt creation, corruption, regeneration, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi> (▿)</p>
            <p>Made by IOHN WOOLTON Miniſter of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Thomas Purfoote, dwelling in <hi>Paules Churchyard at the ſigne of the</hi> Lucrece. Anno Dom. 1576.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:20974:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20974:2"/>
            <head>To the right vvorshipfull <hi>William Moune</hi> Eſquire, Iohn Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton wyſheth proſperous ſucceſſe in all vvorldly affayres, and in the life to come, Ioyes, and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall felicitie.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOSE THAT HAVE</hi> imployed their ſtudies and labors, in the diligent inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and deſcription of <hi>Anatomie,</hi> howe the partes of mans body are coupled &amp; knitte together, vvhat properties and powers they haue, vvhat things are healthfull, or hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto the ſame: haue alwayes purchaſed great prayſe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gst all honeſt &amp; vertuous men. And although it be accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of ſome, an yrkeſome and cruell thing, to cut and mangle mans lymmes and members: yet<note place="margin">The know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomy pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitable for mans lyfe.</note> the ende and vſe of the ſame is both neceſſarie and profitable, in all the courſe and trade of mans life. The cauſe vvhy thoſe thinges are ſo ſtudiouſly ſought after, is, that ſalues and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines may be more commodiouſly and skilfully applied and miniſtred vnto liuing bodies. For how, or to vvhat ende can they vſe applications
<pb facs="tcp:20974:3"/> to any part, if they knowe not the poſition, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, propertie, and nature thereof?</p>
            <p>Beſides this commoditie, the inspection of<note place="margin">The know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomy doe induce vs to thinke y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> there is a God. Galen vſu part. &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lijs locis. Iob. 10. 37 38. 39. Pſa. 19. 33 133. Wyſd. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Anatomie</hi> (as <hi>Galene</hi> diuinely writeth) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth the creature, to ſome knowledge of his Creator. And euen ſo <hi>Iob, Dauid, Salomon,</hi> &amp; many other in the holy Scripture, after they haue moued vs to beholde the glory of God, by his handy vvorkes: vvhen they come to the vewe and conſideration of mans body, they ſo ſpeake therof in vvay of admiration and vvon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, that vve may vvell gather the ſtraunge and almoſt diuine compoſition of the ſame, very much to excell all other earthly creatures.</p>
            <p>Nowe if men for the declaration of theſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things, haue bin always heretofore ſo well loued &amp; liked: Then thoſe can not be miſliked,<note place="margin">The conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all anatomy and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> fruite thereof.</note> that in a generall Anatomie of vvhole man, aſwell of his ſoule, as of his body, doo endeuer to deſcribe mans excellencie before his fall, and his miſerable ruine, together with the cauſes and conſequences therof. And then deſcende in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Regeneration and reſtitution of Gods I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in man, vvherby the Chriſtian liueth, eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by death: his body ſhall riſe agayne, and bee coupled vvith the ſoule, and ſo at the laſt bee
<pb facs="tcp:20974:3"/> glorified eternally in the heauenly kingdome.</p>
            <p>But vve can haue no helpe in the doctrine of theſe high myſteries, neither of <hi>Hypocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of the ſe thinges commeth out of gods word.</note> 
               <hi>Galene,</hi> nor any other bodily Phiſition: for they conteyne them ſelues vvithin the limits of their profeſſion. Thoſe Scriptures then, which be called (and are in deede) Holy, doo playnly reuele this doctrine vnto vs: fir thoſe that haue excelled in vvitte, learning, and iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Heathen, vewing the conpoſition of man, vvere euen amaſed, in conſidering princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally two things. First, that amongst all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall<note place="margin">Man part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, partly y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> fouleſt of viſible cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures.</note> and viſible creatures in this vvorlde, there vvas none ſo fayre and beautifull in witte, accions, and ſtature of body. Secondly, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst all the ſayde creatures, there vvas none founde ſubiect to ſo many miſeries and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. For this noble and excellent nature of man decayeth muche more horribly, then an Oxe, or an aſſe: and nature abhorreth mans carkas more then any other liuing creatures: and if it be not interred and buried, there will Serpentes, and Todes, quickly ſpring out of the ſame, as experience hath often times declared.</p>
            <p>But from whence man hath contracted ſuch excellency on thone ſide, and ſuch deformitie
<pb facs="tcp:20974:4"/> &amp; deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on thother ſide: theſe wiſe world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings<note place="margin">The Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niks know the diſeaſe of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but they know not y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> cauſe.</note> were not able, with any wiſedome to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire and find out. For as S. Aug. well ſayth, <hi>They felt the diſeaſe of our nature: But the cauſe they knew not.</hi> God therfore of his infinite and great mercy, hath comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the holy ſcripture, the hiſtory and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of theſe greate matters, out of whome I haue drawen this briefe abſtract of Anatomie. And albeit I acknowledge willingly my owne<note place="margin">Aug. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Iulia. lib. 4. ca. 14.</note> imbecilitie, and do confeſſe that many are fitter for this matter then my ſelfe: yet becauſe it is the duety of a minſter of Gods worde, to poynt (as it were) with the finger, out of that riche ſtore and treaſure of the holy ſcripture, what men ought to thinke and hold of ſuch neceſſary matters: I ſhall be accompted (I truſt) neither arrogant, nor preſumptuous, in handling thoſe thinges which are within the precinct of my of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and calling. And for that by experience I right well knowe (if any other) howe buſie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayners will be with my phraſe, ſtile and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode, yet becauſe many of them haue ben long hatching their adled egges, &amp; haue yet brought forth nothing: Let them now finiſh their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> karping other mens good endeuours:
<pb facs="tcp:20974:4"/> ſurely they ſhall ſoner pyne away with their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and enuy, then feare me from honeſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, to do good to my countrey. Let them not ſpare their Chriſtall eyes on Gods name to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend my wordes and matter, my inuention, definitions, and diuiſions: yea if they will they may note the eſcapes in the impreſsion. &amp;c. It ſhall be ſufficient vnto me, if the Chriſtian rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, will conſter well my good intent: Being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of opinion for my owne parte, that none can excuſe his idlenes, that may be profitable any wayes to others.</p>
            <p>Now for that this weake and ſeely Anatomie was loth to go abroad without ſome eſpecial pro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I haue ſelected your worſhip to be a Patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſame: Moued therevnto with that great curteſie and goodwill, which from your firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with me, you haue ſhewed towarde me. Moreouer your ardent zeale and loue of the gospell ſomewhat emboldned me in this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, which amongſt many other your comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations cheefly commendeth you. It is a greate matter to come of a greate parentage, to haue large hereditamentes and poſſeſsions, wherein none at all in Cornwayll doo paſſe you, and very fewe are comparable with you: But with thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:20974:5"/> thinges, to be the ſeruaunt of Chriſte, a louer of his gospell, and a foſter, &amp; nurce to his church, (as you and that vertuous gentlewoman your Wyfe, are well knowen to be in your countrey) is,<note place="margin">Hom. in aliqu. ſcrip tos locos.</note> as <hi>Baſilius Magnus</hi> ſayth, moſt laudable. In the which, and all other vertues, I beſeech God to continue you to your latter ende: and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe you alſo in all vvorldly vvorſhip &amp; dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. From Exceter the .xij. of March.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhippes humblie Iohn Woolton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:20974:5"/>
            <head>The firſt part of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomie, declaring the ſtate of man <hi>before his fall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T IS BOTH TRV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Cicero his ſentence of mans ſoule. De finibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> liber. 1. &amp; Tuſ. queſt. li. 1. &amp;. 3. &amp;. 5.</note> and excellently vvrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Cicero,</hi> not onely the beſt Orator, but the beſt Philoſopher amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the Latin vvriters: <hi>If vve vvere borne &amp; brought foorth into this vvorlde ſuche perſons that vve could vewe Nature, vve ſhould neede neither learning nor instructions, becauſe nature her ſelfe ſhould abundantly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vs.</hi> But nowe there are lefte vnto vs certayne ſedes or ſparkes of vertue, which we ouer haſtely quenche with corrupte conditions, and peruers opinions, that the light of Nature can not any vvhere<note place="margin">Nature yel deth to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> ſhevve it ſelfe: For veritie giueth place to vanitie, and nature eftſoones yeeldeth to corrupt and preiudicate opinions. In the which wordes the Diuine writer (taught by experience, reaſon, and learning) ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth that nature hath yet left in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde ſome ſmall power and operation,
<pb facs="tcp:20974:6"/> whiche he nameth ſparkes or ſeedes of vertue, meaning no doubt, the ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the harte and conſcience, and the light of the will &amp; vnderſtanding, which by corruption of nature are ſo blotted and ſhadovved in vs, that vvee can not beholde our Creator, neither yet ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſee what is conuenient and honeſt in a morall life, vvhich the ſecond Table propoſeth vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Before the fall of our Parentes, when<note place="margin">Mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture before his fall.</note> nature was innocent &amp; vncorrupted, this light of vviſedome, and intelligence of things diuine and humaine, did ſhyne brightly in man: neither had he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only ſparks &amp; ſedes, but a plentiful ſtorehouſe &amp; flowing fountaine of all vertue: which the ſame author ſeemeth to haue ſene in a glimmes, whiles that he ſpeaketh after this maner: <hi>Mannes mynde beeing dery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cic. tuſ. 1. &amp;. 4.</note> 
               <hi>from the Diuine minde, may not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vvith any other thing</hi> (if I may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſaye ſo) <hi>but with God him ſelfe. Which Minde if it be ſo instructed, and as it vvere cured, that it be not ſeduced with er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, then is it a perfect minde, that is to ſay, abſolute reaſon, whiche is all one with vertue.</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:20974:6"/> Cicero ſeemeth to haue receyued this<note place="margin">Cicero hys ſpeeche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſcripture.</note> opinion from the auncient writers: For in that he ſayth our minds are taken out of the heauenly Minde, it is that which the ſcripture vttereth: <hi>And God inspired into man a liuing Soule.</hi> And vvheras he ſayeth, that it maye in ſome ſorte bee compared vnto God him ſelfe, he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that vvhiche the Scripture ſayth: <hi>And God created manne after his owne ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude.</hi> And vvhereas he ſayeth, that yf it vvere inſtructed and cured in ſuche ſorte, that it mighte not be blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vvith the darkeneſſe of Errors: he meaneth, if ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had not ſo filthely fallen, it ſhould haue bene a perfect minde, and an abſolute reaſon, that is, a ſincere and vncorrupt nature. But the ſame Wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpeaketh more playnely hereof in annother place, after thys manner:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is there (J vvyll not ſaye in Man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicero lib. de legibus.</note> 
               <hi>but thoroughoute Heauen and Earth) more Diuine then Reaſon? Which vvhen it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to perfection, it is very apte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y named Wyſedome. Seeinge then that Reaſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth bothe in God, and Manne, and that there is nothing more diuine then the ſame: it
<pb facs="tcp:20974:7"/> followeth that through reaſon onely there is a communion or partaking betwene God &amp; m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n: and amongest vvhom reaſon is common, right reaſon is alſo common. Whereof it followeth that thoſe onely doo knowe God, vvho vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande and conſider their origine and of spring.</hi> By theſe and ſuche other like ſentences we may ſee hovve the Philoſophers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating of the excellencie of mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, did geſſe, (and as it vvere dreame) of the diuine qualities and operations of Mans ſoule in the ſtate of Innocencie: Which they named a good capitayne &amp;<note place="margin">Mans ſoule in the ſtate of innocency a good cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne or guide to liue well.</note> guyde to liue vvell and bleſſedly, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing vs that we ſhould not extinguish and obſcure the ſame vvith corrupt opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and peruers maners: but rather ſtirre vp and perfectly confirme the ſame vvith laudable exerciſes, and wholſome inſtructions and documents.</p>
            <p>But leſt any man ſhoulde ſay that I diſcourſe ſuch great &amp; weightie matters, proper vnto the diuines, vvith the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of Ethnicks and heathen Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers: let him alſo conſider that S. Paul, that elect veſſell of ſaluation, to haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of mans firſt eſtate
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20974:7"/> notably, yea and almoſte ſenſibly, after this maner: <hi>For vvhen the Gentiles vvhich</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> 
               <hi>haue not the lawe, doo of nature the thinges conteyned in the lawe, then they hauing not the lawe, are a lawe vnto them ſelues, vvhich ſhew the deedes of the lawe written in their hartes: vvhiles their conſcience beareth vvitneſſe vnto them, and alſo their thoughts accuſing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or excuſing them.</hi> In the vvhich vvords<note place="margin">Man in the ſtate of inno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cency a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tſchole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter to him ſelfe.</note> the Apoſtle playnly declareth, hovv that God in the creation of man planted, and as it vvere ingraffed a kinde of diuine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and perfect povver: wherby vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further helpe of externall doctors or doctrine, he vvas both able to fulfil gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements, and alſo to be a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient lawe and ſcholemaſter to himſelfe, whiles that his ovvne thoughts and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per conſcience giueth true verdites, and pronounceth iuſte iudgement vnto him in all his accions and cogitations.</p>
            <p>This excellent eſtate and perfect ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue inſpired into man by God in creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which novve (more is the pitie) is loſte and extinguished, maye the better bee knowen by the nature &amp; diſpoſition of brute beaſtes, vnto whom with indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:20974:8"/> the holy ſcripture ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs. For that wiſe and omnipotent Creator hath expreſſed his heauenly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome<note place="margin">A plaine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, by a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſon of the nature of brute <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſtes.</note> in al his works, as Cicero right wel ſayth, and hath giuen to all liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures both abilitie and inſtrumentes to execute their operations and functions. And although the power of brute beaſts together with the nature and efficacie of all naturall thinges, by meanes of mans rebellion agaynſt his God, are vvonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully impaired, yet wee may ſee alſo by compariſon from them, the ſteppes and print of diuine qualities in mannes na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: whereof Tullie according to his<note place="margin">Cic. tuſ. 5.</note> manner ſpeaketh as followeth: <hi>From whence may we more aptly take our begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning then from nature her ſelfe the common Parent of vs all? Who not onely in all liuing</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nature the common pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of all thing.</note> 
               <hi>creatures, but alſo in Trees, Plantes, and Herbes, hath in euery of their kindes wrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght perfection. And therefore aſwell Trees and Vines, as alſo thoſe thinges vvhiche are more baſe and lower; haue their conueniencie, for ſome are alwayes freſhe and greene, and ſome beeing bare in the vvinter, in the ſpring time beeing comforted, and as it vvere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20974:8"/> vvith the heate of the ſunne, doo ſhoote foorth their bloſſomes agayne. Neither is there any thing ſo mute and cloſely created, but that ſometyme it geueth foorth a ſhewe of his nature, and beareth eyther flowres, or fruite, or beries, or ſheweth ſome one thinge or other, vvhereby his propertie and qualitie maye bee knowen. But if vvee proceede fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to beholde the nature of beastes, albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it bruite and vnreaſonable, yet becauſe they haue ſence in them, their powers and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may bee more eaſily conſidered. For Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nature hath giuen to dyuers beaſtes dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</note> 
               <hi>hath appoynted ſome beastes to liue in the vvater, ſome to flye at pleaſure in the wide ayre, ſome to creepe vppon the grounde, ſome to vvalke, ſome to vvander by them ſelues, ſome vvilde, ſome tame: and finally other ſome to lye hidde couered in the earth. Nowe euery one of theſe, for that they can not vſurpe the trade and condition of other kindes, do conteine them ſelues within the incloſiers of their owne Natures. And as euery beast hath his ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and proper, eyther inclination or condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and reteyneth the ſame: ſo hath man his nature muche more diuine and excellent, if we may call thoſe thinges excellent that are ſo by compariſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20974:9"/>
            <p>We ſee then by the vewe and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of brute beaſtes, that they had in the beginning, and yet retayne that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination vvhiche is apt and conuenient to their natures, in procreating, in cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, and in defending them ſelues and<note place="margin">A ſpeciall diſpoſition of ſome par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticuler li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> their young ones. The oxe, the ſheepe, the henne, vvith many other beaſtes and birdes, doo knovve their peculier foſter and frend: they make neſtes and dennes for them ſelues and their iſſue. And if we beholde the nature, or rather the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth of Emets and Bees, we ſhall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any great difficultie perceyue that god hath inſpired into them a farre more<note place="margin">Man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the nature of brute bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes. <hi>Jere. 1.</hi>
               </note> excellent nature. All vvhich thinges the Scripture oftentimes incultateth to our confuſion &amp; ſhame, ſending vs to them, that vve may the rather knovv our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and rebellion. The Oxe (ſayth the Prophet) knovveth his ovvner, and the Aſſe his maſters cribbe, but my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hath not knovven mee. And agayne: The Storke and the Svvalovve haue kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen their tyme, and goo thou ſluggard vnto the Emmet. By the compariſon then of very brute beaſtes, vnto vvhom
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20974:9"/> God hath giuen in eche of their kindes an apte conueniencie to execute thoſe qualities miraculouſly infuſed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by God: we may in ſome part perceyue the heauenly and diuine nature of Man, to bee muche more noble and excellent,<note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> vnto whom the mighty God gaue power and dominion ouer all earthly creatures, and made him lorde and ruler ouer the workes of his hands, breathing into him a reaſonable ſoule, and fashioning him after his ovvne ſimilitude and likenes.</p>
            <p>Theſe bleſsings ſo plentifully povvred vpon man by almightie god, hath cauſed men vveerie of this vvorlde, and greedie gaping after heauenly thinges, to breake out into theſe vvordes: <hi>Examine (I har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily</hi>
               <note place="margin">Melan. de anima &amp; in locis com.</note> 
               <hi>pray you) vvhat is that image of God in Man. It is Gods good pleaſure that mans mind ſhould be as it vvere a glaſſe vvherein vve may beholde him. His vvill is that man ſhould bee like bookes, vvherein he vvould vvrite his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vvith his owne fingers. Theſe vvonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thinges vve learne and conſider in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of mans mind. Neither is there any eloquence, eyther of men or of Angels, that is able condingly to expreſſe that great honor and
<pb facs="tcp:20974:10"/> dignity, wherwith God hath adorned &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified vs, in imparting to vs his owne ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and likeneſse.</hi> Whereby he had power<note place="margin">Mans po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer before his fall.</note> to thinke and vvill of all thinges, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of his creator, which gods pleaſure was to haue him vvill &amp; thinke, hauing as Tertullian writeth, the ſame ſenſes &amp;<note place="margin">Tert. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionem.</note> motions which god himſelf had: which things vvere ſo naturall in our firſte pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, as mans eye doth ſee &amp; behold ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects. In the vvhich vvords albeit fewe &amp;<note place="margin">Luthe. in Geneſim.</note> ſhort, vve haue an euident and plaine deſcription of perfitte nature, vvhereof the philoſophers did rather diuine and dreame, then knovve any thing effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, to vvitte, that it vvas the ſincere eye of the ſoule, alvvayes fixed vppon, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dazeled or dimmed vvith errors, but poynting vnto man alvvayes, as it vvere vvith a finger, both the maieſtie of god, and perſvvading him to followe his precepts and commaundements.<note place="margin">The neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of this doctrine.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The doctrine therfore of the image of god in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is very needfull in the church of god: both becauſe it propoſeth vnto vs euident teſtimonies of gods fauour &amp; loue tovvarde mankinde, and declareth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20974:10"/> the excellent eſtate of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before his fall, in the which god did as it were ſtampe &amp; imprint the radiant beames of his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, rectitude and liberty of will, that man might be his mancion place and temple: Vnto vvhom as he purpoſed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate bleſſedneſſe and felicitie, ſo he required at his hands againe to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced and vvorshipped. Moreouer it doth not onely deſcribe the eſtate &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1. 2. Co. 4. Heb. 1.</note> of the firſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but it doth alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the abominablenes of ſin, how the image of god was corrupt in mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; therwithall sheweth holſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies by the ſon of god, who is the very perfect &amp; ſubſtantiall image of god the father, reſtoring to thoſe that be regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate through the holy ghoſt, the created Image of god blemished in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Of the which image of god created, I meane to write ſome thing at this preſent, if not ſo much as the mater requireth, yet ſo farre forth as in this imbecility of our nature, we may by the helpe of gods ſpirit ſelect out of the holy ſcriptures. And for that through ignorance of words, as Ariſtotle ſaith, men often times erre in the truth
<pb facs="tcp:20974:11"/> of matters, I vvill firſt examine the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of the vvorde, that my Treatiſe may be leſſe intricate for my Reader to conceyue, and more facile for my ſelfe to proſecute.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Imago,</hi> in Englishe an Image, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth<note place="margin">Of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> word Image or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imilitude.</note> generally a repreſentation or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trature of any thing which is made ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by creation or cogitation, or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or propagatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eyther in paynting or grauing, or by any other meanes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed after the example of an other<note place="margin">Gene. 1.</note> matter. Moſes ſayth that man was made after the image and ſimilitude of God. Almightie God then is the liuely exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple after whom man vvas created, that he might in certayne properties of hys whole ſubſtance expreſſe him. The ſonne of God vvas not made after the image of his father, as the auncient Fathers haue right well obſerued, but he was begotten of God the father, and is the coeſſentiall &amp; the eternall Image of the euerlaſting father. The Hebrewes vſe the worde <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> for an Image, and <hi>Demuth</hi> for a ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, the whiche the Grecians expreſſe in <hi>eikona kai omoioſin.</hi> But the lerned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20974:11"/> doo vſe theſe vvordes indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For in the ſame text where this worke<note place="margin">Calu. Inſt. lib. 1. Gene. 1.</note> of God is repeated, Moſes ſpeaketh af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this maner: <hi>And God created man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. &amp;c.</hi> And agayne he vſeth onely one of the words, God created man after his<note place="margin">Gene. 5.</note> ovvne ſimilitude. By this repetition of one and the ſelfe ſame thing, whiche is expreſſed onely in one vvorde: one and the ſelfe ſame thing is deſcribed.</p>
            <p>Notvvithſtanding I will not hide from<note place="margin">A differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betweene i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage &amp; ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude.</note> my louing Reader the difference whiche certayne notable and famous expoſitors of the holy Scriptures haue put betwene the vvordes Image, and ſimilitude. Saint Auguſtine ſayth: <hi>The Soule is like vnto God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex Augu. de quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te anim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>for it is made immortall and indiſſoluble. The worde Image therefore apperteyneth vnto the forme, and ſimilitude vnto nature.</hi> And an excellent man of our time: <hi>An Image is</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Mar. in cap. 1. Gene.</note> 
               <hi>an outworde bodely forme or faſhion, expreſſing or repreſenting any man: but a ſimilitude is a qualitie of the minde whiche we imitate and followe.</hi> And that famous clarke Luther vvriteth thus: Albeit almoſt all the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<note place="margin">Luth. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. 5. Ge.</note> doo take the wordes Image &amp; ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude for one thing, yet in reading of
<pb facs="tcp:20974:12"/> things I haue noted ſome difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvveene thoſe vvordes. For Zelim ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth properly an image or figure: As vvhen the ſcripture ſayth, <hi>deſtroy the aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of your images.</hi> In that place the word ſignifieth nothing els then pictures and images, which were ſet vp. But <hi>Demuth</hi> vvhich is a ſimilitude, is the perfection of the image: as for example. When vve ſpeake of a deade image ſtamped in coyne or money, vve ſaye this is the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the king or queene: But that i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage hathe not the ſimilitude, neither doth it ſhew the liniaments and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. In that Moſes ſayth therfore, <hi>that man was made after Gods ſimilitude,</hi> he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vveth, that man doth not onely repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent god, in that he hath reaſon and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, but alſo that he hath ſuche intelligence and vvill, vvhereby he both perfectly knevv god, and alſo had a will to execute gods commaundement. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome there be that ſaye, that gods image reſteth in mans ſubſtance, and the ſimilitude in the accidentes. Let euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enioy his ovvne cogitations, I am of this opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that bicauſe Moſes deſcribing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20974:12"/> this notable vvorke of god ſomtime vſed one vvord ſometime another, that both theſe wordes are vſed for better decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, playnely to expreſſe one thing.<note place="margin">Two ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> image of God.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This one thing I thinke more conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to be conſidered in the entry of this matter, that the image of god in the holy ſcripture is attributed both to the onely begotten ſonne of god, Ieſus Chriſt, and to godly men, his ſonnes by adoption: But in diuerſe conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. It is vvritten of the onely begotten ſon<note place="margin">Colo. 1.</note> of god: <hi>Who is the image of the inuiſible god, the firſt begotten before all creatures.</hi> And in<note place="margin">2. Co. 4.</note> another place, <hi>Chriſt is the image of God.</hi> In theſe places Chriſt is called the image of God, in reſpect of his heauenly father.<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.</note> And therfore he ſayth: <hi>Philip, he that hath ſeene me, hath ſeene the father,</hi> ſhevving that his father is knovven, in and onelye<note place="margin">Now chriſt is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> image of God, &amp; how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is the image of God.</note> through him. Our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt then is the totall, and coeſſentiall image of God his father, of lyke maieſtie and glory: For ſo he pronounceth of hym ſelfe, ſaying, <hi>I and the father am one:</hi> &amp; the Apoſtle: <hi>who is the brightneſſe of his glory, and the image of hys ſubstaunce, bearing
<pb facs="tcp:20974:13"/> all thinges vvith the vvorde of his power.</hi> But vvhen man is named the Image of God, it is not ment that he is all one vvith the<note place="margin">Gene. 1. Coloſ. 3. 1. Cor. 11.</note> ſonne of God, but that he is his Image create, Gratuite by grace or adoption, muche inferior to the naturall image Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte. And yet it is not to be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any ſmal prerogatiue that man and Angels ſeuerally, aboue all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, haue this title and dignitie giuen vnto them, that they haue and beare the ſimilitude and image of the liuing God, of the which ſeconde Image, I vvill only write at this preſent.</p>
            <p>What this Image of God is in man, there are diuers opinions amongeſt the auncient vvriters. Theodoretus citeth<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theodret. queſt. 20. in Gene.</hi> what this Image of God in man is</note> ſundry of them in his queſtions vppon Geneſis. Firſt, ſome ſayd that the Image of God is that vvhich is inuiſible in the ſoule. Secondly, ſome ſayd that mannes body is that Image: whiche opinion he aſcribeth to one Milito. Thirdly, ſome ſayde that whole man vvas the Image of God, becauſe he is placed as it were in the middle betvveene all creatures com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact of body and ſoule. Fourthly, ſome
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20974:13"/> affirmed the image of God in man, to be nothing els but that power &amp; autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie which he hath ouer al worldly crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And finally he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cludeth, that this image of god is in the reaſonable ſoule,<note place="margin">Aug. li. 14 detrinitate ca. 8. Pet. Mar. in. 1. cap. gen. et. in locis com. lo. xij. fol. 101. Cal. lib. 1. inst. Luth. in. gen. ca. 1.</note> vanderſtanding, iudging, and executing things iuſtly. Saint Auguſtine ſometime taketh this Image of God to be the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſubſtance of the ſoule, minde, and wil, ſometime the qualities of the ſame. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine acknowlegeth the image of God moſte cleerely to ſhine in mannes ſoule, and yet to ſhew it ſelfe in the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and in all powers of the ſame. Luther that excellent writer, defineth, or rather deſcribeth this image after this maner: <hi>The image of god, after the which Adam was created, was a matter moſt noble &amp; excellent: For as yet no leproſie of ſinne had infected ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <note place="margin">whether man is the image of God in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his ſoule or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, or of both.</note> 
               <hi>the minde or will. But all the interior and exterior ſenſes were pure and cleane. For the vnderſtanding was moſt pure, memorie prompt and ready, the will ſincere, resting in a diuine ſecuritie, without penſiue thought or dreadfull feare of death. Herevnto was annexed a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table beauty and comelineſſe of all the externall members of the body, wherein man paſſed and
<pb facs="tcp:20974:14"/> ſurmounted all other inferior Creatures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And albeit hee vvryteth that the<note place="margin">Arabian hereſie.</note> Image of God is in the vvhole manne, both in bodye and ſoule: yet he vvas farre, aſvvell from the Arabyan hereſie, vvhich vvas <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 230. as from the Anthropomorphites, and other Monkes<note place="margin">Anthropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphites.</note> of Aegypt, who affyrmed this image to be onely in the body, becauſe the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture oftentimes maketh mention of the face, eyes, eares, noſe, handes, and feete of God. Whiche phraſes the Scripture vndoubtedly vſeth onely for our capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, and better vnderſtanding: for tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Goddes ſubſtance, our Sauiour Chryſte playnely affyrmeth him to bee a ſpirite: And I knovve that ſome ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.</note> learned Writers haue acquited the Anthropomorphites from ſuche groſſe opinions, and that they had a farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſence in thoſe phraſes.</p>
            <p>The reaſon that maketh many men ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre,<note place="margin">Doubtes anſwered &amp; reſolued touching this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> yea &amp; deteſt this poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Luthers,</hi> that the image of God in man conſiſteth both in the body &amp; ſoule, is this: <hi>God is not any corporall ſubſtance: therfore no part of his image ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be in any corporall ſubſtance.</hi> But we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20974:14"/> muſt conſider that whole man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſting of body &amp; ſoule, was faſhioned after the Image &amp; likenes of God. Moreouer the perfection of mans corporal ſubſtance, &amp; the proportion or apt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniency ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with the ſoule, which was appoynted to expreſſe his powers to the organical or external inſtruments of the body: and Immortalitie vvhiche vvas alſo giuen to this corporal matter, did clerly expres &amp; repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſome portion of gods image. Albeit therfore it can not be denied, but that the cheefe &amp; principall degrees of this diuine Image is in mans ſoule, as in the moſt noble and excellent part: yet the body ſo diuinely vnited vnto the ſoule, and indued with ſuch notable or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namentes, is not to be defrauded of that which of right ought to be yeelded vnto it. So that as thoſe doo offende in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, that aſcribe this image of God to mans body onely: ſo doo they alſo erre in defect, that place it only in the mind. For that the holy ſcripture eftſones repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that God made not onely mannes Soule, but whole man after his owne ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude and likenes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20974:15"/>
            <p>It vvas the vvil and pleaſure of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<note place="margin">The duetie of man in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe things.</note> God, that through this his Image tranfuſed into man, he might both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent and expreſſe his maker, and be obedient vnto him: appoynting man (as I ſayde before) to be as a glaſſe, wherin he woulde ſhine and be ſeene, and as a booke vvherein vvith his ovvne finger he would vvrite his vviſdome. Teaching vs in this image vvhat God is, to vvitte, an eternall and euerlaſting minde: and what maner of God he is, namely, vviſe and true, louing chaſtiſtie and iuſtice, of a free povver, embracing men vvith a fatherly affection, he beeing the creator, and they his creatures: requiring of vs that our minde and vvill ſhould accorde vvith his vvill and commaundement. And this is that vvonderfull vviſdome, iuſtice, goodnes, and povver of his: which his pleaſure vvas to be read and knowen in the conſideration and contemplation of man, vvhom he made of ſuche excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie that he vvas capable of his Image, that in his ſoule and body, and in all his interior and exterior povvers and acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he might shevve foorth ſome like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20974:15"/> of God, but fynyte, and ſuche as vvas conuenient for a creature.</p>
            <p>This Image of God in man gratuite or create, had before his fall many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent qualities. Firſt, in reſpect of the Minde, Will, and Harte, vvherein vvas a maruellous diuine Harmonie and conſente. Sainct Auguſtine vvente a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout<note place="margin">Augu. lib. 14. de Tr. cap. 8.</note> too shevve the difference of the three perſons in Trinitie, by the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of this Image of god in man: <hi>Jn manne</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>there bee three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall</hi>
               <note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of man before hys fall.</note> 
               <hi>thinges, The Minde begetting or bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Cogitation. And the cogitation, vvhich is the Jmage of the thing cogitated: And the Will, vvherein there is both ioy and loue.</hi> Theſe three things he applieth after this maner: <hi>The eternall Father ſignifieth the Minde begetting in Cogitation the eternall word, the ſecond perſon in Trinitie. The Jmage formed in cogitation, ſignifieth the ſonne of God: And the Will ſhadoweth the holye Ghoste.</hi> This collation muſte needes bee pleaſaunt to humble Mindes: For therein vvee ſee that man is appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bee a teſtimonie of God, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that hee is an Eſſence intelligible
<pb facs="tcp:20974:16"/> and mouing him ſelfe. And although ſainct Auguſtine doo vnderſtande the image of God in manne, of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of the Soule, Minde, and Will: yet all the learned menne almoſte doo comprehende the gyftes together vvith the ſubſtaunce, or as they vſually ſpeake, the vertues of perfect Nature in eche parte of the Soule, agreeing vvith the diuine Mynde. For ſo ſainct Paule in the vvorde Image vnderſtoode not onely mans ſubſtaunce, but the gyftes or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvers vvherein ſuche vertues doo ſhine as are conſonante vvith the minde di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine: whiche giftes were diſtinct and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable from the ſubſtaunce it ſelfe, as it is manyfeſt by mans fall, vvherein theſe excellent proprieties vvere loſte, the ſubſtaunce of the Minde, Wyll, and Harte, vnto thys day abyding and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning.</p>
            <p>But to returne to theſe excellent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties<note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of mans mind</note> of the ſoule before mans fall: There ſhyned a cleare light in mannes Minde, to vvitte, a perfecte knovvledge of God, and a communication of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine wiſdome, whereby he knewe both
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20974:16"/> Gods ſubſtance and will: And alſo that man was to this ende created, that not only this knowlege might ſhine in him: but alſo that he ſhoulde with a grateful willing mind ſhew obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Beſides this knowledge of all diuine things which were nedeful to man in the ſeruice of God, and toward the attayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of eternal life: the Lorde endewed him with a right excellent knowlege of matters Morall and Natural, that he was able to conceiue the qualities and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of all liuing thinges. So that as ſoone as he ſawe Eua, he ſayd by and by, <hi>This is bone of my bone, and fleſh of my fleſh: and ſhe ſhall be called Virago, becauſe ſhe was taken of the Man.</hi> He vvas profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeene in Philoſophie, as it appeareth by the Hiſtorie of Creation: vvherein we reade hovve he gaue names to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry liuing creature according to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and qualities.</p>
            <p>In mans will there was a conuerſion to<note place="margin">Mans wil.</note> god, that is to ſay, an vniuerſal obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to his lavve, hauing an ardent loue of God, and all vertues: flagrante, bent, and directe to that ende, that the firſte
<pb facs="tcp:20974:17"/> example might be knovven and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: &amp; therwith was annexed a libertie in all accions, that he might both shewe vnto god willing obedience, and alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde all thinges vvith iudgement that were diſpleaſant to his Creator.</p>
            <p>In the hart all affections and appeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hart and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</note> did obey his minde &amp; will, neither was there diſſétion in any thing. So that there vvas a Diuine harmonie of the minde, will, and harte. For as the minde did rightly knovve god and his wyll: ſo the hart &amp; the wil did thinke one thing, he loued god earneſtly, neither was there any thing in mans nature which was not pure, holy, &amp; ſincere. And euery orgaine parte and inſtrument of mans ſubſtance had facultie and readineſſe infuſed into them by god, that they vvere both vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and hable to doo the thinges requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by god at their hands, which god ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the law of obedience had im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>printed, and as it were ſtamped in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable natures.</p>
            <p>There was alſo in this image of god in<note place="margin">Man had a lordſhip o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer al wiling creatures.</note> man, a preheminencie &amp; ſuperioritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other inferior creatures, whom he excelled many wayes, both in reaſon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20974:17"/> and quicknes of ſenſes, aſwell in forme and ſtature of body vpright &amp; looking towarde heauen, as alſo in agilitie and mobilitie of accions, and eſpecially in that ſoueraigne power and dominion which he had ouer all inferior creatures, as it were an Emperour ouer his ſubiects. For as God is the vniuerſall Lorde, king, and gouernour ouerall creatures: euen ſo it pleaſed him to collate vnto man a certayn dominion particular &amp; limited, vnto whom they would haue yeelded o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience gladly, &amp; haue reputed him for gods Lieuetenant, if he had reteined the image of god in him ſincere and vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted: which dominion albeit by our ruine it be exceedingly impaired in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, yet it is ſomwhat reſtored by faith. <hi>Thou ſhalt treade vpon the Adder and Coca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91. Great bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ruled by little children.</note> Daniell was caſt to the Lions: The Lord prayeth with the wild beaſtes in the wildernes: Paule was not hurt of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſon &amp; Dauid ouercame lions: and we may daily ſee litle childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a ſticke to rule huge &amp; mighty bodied beaſtes, through the maieſty of gods image, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che yet after a ſort ſhineth in man, and is very fearfull and terrible vnto them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20974:18"/>
            <p>Herevnto vve may adde mans authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<note place="margin">Mans be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning &amp; ende.</note> &amp; preheminence in conſideration of his beginning, coueniencie, and ende: For as god is the beginning of all things in creation, ſo is Adam the beginning of all men by generation: And as god hath a conueniency with all thinges, and all thinges ought to looke vpon God: So is man <hi>microcoſmos,</hi> that is to ſay, a little vvorld, and a lord in reſpecte of inferior creatures, that they all should reuerence and honor him. And as God is the ende of all thinges: So is man the ende of all inferior creatures, they beeing made for mans ſake, that he might be a ruler ouer<note place="margin">Sap. 2.</note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And according to the wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>moderate &amp; gouerne the round worlde in equity &amp; iuſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally this image had an aſſured hope<note place="margin">Mans im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality.</note> of immortality, that his life shoulde be bleſſed &amp; eternall, not ſubiect to death. For the diuinity it ſelf is immortal, after<note place="margin">Gen. 3. 5.</note> the which as the ſcripture ſaith, <hi>man was created.</hi> If therfore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had not fallen into ſin, this nature &amp; bleſſed eſtate in creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had indured for euer, it should neuer haue ben we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke or old, it shuld not haue ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed with heauines or diſeaſes: But yet liuing in Paradiſe, shoulde haue
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20974:18"/> ben the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce tranſlated into the celeſtial &amp; ſpirituall life. And vnto this image God added ouer &amp; beſides the bleſſings afore mencioned, a certen &amp; eſpeciall kinde of<note place="margin">If m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> had not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned he ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de haue b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ute et Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe into heauen.</note> worshipping of god, exacting an obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto the ſame, in propoſing vnto him that law of the tree of knowledge of good &amp; euill: In the which he gaue vnto man, formed after his image, as it were a reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance that he should be both obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfull vnto him for his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings: and that he would afterward tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate him vnto the place of endleſſe ioy &amp; felicity, where he might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the very eſſentiall image of God moſt brightly shining in his ſon our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſte. So that immortality being annexed in the tre of life, did both<note place="margin">Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</note> admonish ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inhabiting this elimentall regio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and being endued vvith profou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de knovvledge of things diuine &amp; humaine that he should vſe that tree as a remedy againſt ſicknes, diſeaſes, &amp; mortality it ſelf: and thervvithal that he should have a manifeſt aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of a better life: Into the vvhich godly men shoulde be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, out of and aboue all elimentall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, vvherin he might behold god face to face, inioying infinite bleſſedneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:20974:19"/> where Gods maieſtie ſhalbe all in all, to his glory and our endleſſe comfort. And theſe be the proprieties of the image of God, imprinted and ingraffed in mans ſubſtaunce, at ſuche time as he breathed into him the beames of hys lighte: Whereof it is requiſite that our mindes ſhould be well informed and inſtructed, when we ponder and examine vvith our ſelues, what manner of image that vvas which Adam had, howe it was ſpoyled &amp; defaced in mans fall, after what manner it is repaired in vs by the holy ghoſt, and of the glorious perfection thereof in the world to come.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>¶ The ſecond part of the Anatomy, ſhewing the ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>ſtruction of Gods image in Man.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ECONDARELY LET<note place="margin">How man loſte Gods Image.</note> vs conſider howe this image of God was deſtroyed in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fall: In ſo muche that there ſcarce remaine any remnants of that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20974:19"/> monunent and building of mans beſt eſtate: For when man, who was left in the hands of his owne counſaile, &amp; in the liberty of his will, did eat of the fruit which was forbidden him, and ſhaking off all feare of God (vnto whom all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures owe obedience) did tranſgreſſe his iuſt and good lawe: And being ſeduced with the Dragons voyce, turned him ſelfe ftom God, caſting away all pietie, reuerence and feare, whiche was due to the eternall maieſtie: He then loſt the<note place="margin">The dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wounds which man receiued by tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> image of god, and death ſeazed vppon man, according to the commination of god before vttered, &amp; became the image of the diuell: and ſo loſing the holy ghoſte, hee fell into the horrible wrath of god, and euen then taſted cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten beginnings of the ſame: he ſawe the miſeries of minde, will, and harte, and death euerlaſting, threatned in the lavv: For being infected with the poyſon of ſinne, he coulde not reteyne any longer the image of iuſtice, wiſedome and lyfe, which was ſtamped in him: But whole man vvas miſerably deformed, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and loſt all his ornamentes and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,
<pb facs="tcp:20974:20"/> in ſo much that he who was before in his vvhole ſubſtance, qualities &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, a bright glaſſe of iuſtice and holines: became the maſke and dounghill of the filthy dragon of hell, and the childe of vvrath and euerlaſting death.</p>
            <p>And to deale ſomewhat in perticulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the good thinges and ornamentes<note place="margin">Bonauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura.</note> vvhich our firſte parentes, and all their progeny loſte in this heauy fall and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable shipwracke, vvere partly natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, partly gratuite (and as Bonauenture ſaith) <hi>Man was vtterly ſpoyled of his gratuit gyftes, and wounded in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>naturals:</hi> For in his minde he loſte the perfit knovvledge of his God: So that alvvayes after it was full of darkenes, ignorance, folishneſſe, and rebellion againſte God: And in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and corporall thinges alſo, that light is exceeding shadovved and obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. For who is novve able to diſcerne<note place="margin">woundes in mannes mind.</note> and vevve the nature of lyuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures but halfe ſo well, as vvas out father Adam before his fall.</p>
            <p>The vvill of man alſo quite turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay<note place="margin">woundes in mannes will.</note> from God, loſte all good inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; habilitie to obey him, ſo that we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20974:20"/> feele our ſelues a very conſpiracy &amp; open rebellion againſt his maieſty: as S. Paule dolefully deploreth, ſaying: <hi>I feele in my members another law, fighting againſt the lawe of God: O miſerable man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from the death of this body. &amp;c.</hi> In mans hart the loue of god is vtterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct, and flames of raging affections doe burne, vvhereof almighty god complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in this vviſe: <hi>The lumpe or maſſe of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> 
               <hi>mans harte is euill from his mothers wombe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This deſtruction of Gods image in<note place="margin">woundes in his whole nature.</note> mans nature, and the putting on of the filthie forme of Satan, is plainely ſet foorth in the accions of Adam, ſtreight after his fall, as vvell in him ſelfe, as in all his poſteritie: When as he beeing pricked vvith the ſting of a guilty co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, did both runne avvay from God, and ſavve his miſerable nakedneſſe, whereof he vvas ashamed. For the very nakedneſſe, vvhiche man did ſee in him ſelfe moſt euidently: doth not onely ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the outwarde, but alſo the inwarde deformitie both of body and ſoule. By meanes therefore of Adams fall the image of God vvas deſtroyed in mans
<pb facs="tcp:20974:21"/> nature, all his povvers and faculties were either depraued or vtterly loſte. He vvas ſpoyled of all his gyftes, in minde, will, &amp; hart: And the vvhole maſſe or lumpe of man, was with gods vvrath, with the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the diuell, vvith all ſickneſſe &amp; ſorowes of body &amp; mind corrupt: wher by we to our great grief feele the burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinne, the biting and gnawing of a wounded conſcience, pityfull paſſions of the ſoule, and finally in this vvorlde, the deſtruction and diſſolution of oure bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies into duſt of the earth.</p>
            <p>Theſe euils and greuous woundes A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam<note place="margin">Adam felte y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> greuous ſores and ſmartes of theſe wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> ſavve and felte after he had entred into league and ſociety vvith the diuell: And therwithall taſted of gods horrible vvrath, the pauors and torments of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death, and the ſtrength of the lavve, vvhereof the Apoſtle ſpeaketh: <hi>By the law commeth knowledge of ſinne, and the law worketh wrath:</hi> Through the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vveight of theſe greate dolors and torments, he muſt needes haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently periſhed, and incurred eternall damnation, if the mercifull Lorde had not taken pitty on the miſerie of man,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20974:21"/> by the ſupplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſonne Chriſt, in<note place="margin">Howe Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries was comforted.</note> reſpect of whom he vttered the promiſe of the goſpel, made ioyful mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the bleſſed ſeede of the woman: and turning away his angry countenance, loked vpon man with the eyes of his mercy.</p>
            <p>Beſides al theſe things, Adam ſawe the<note place="margin">Adan ſawe ſome effects of hys ſinne in his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. <hi>Cayne.</hi>
               </note> fruite of his fal, and the deteſtablenes of his offence, not without great ſorow and heauines of hart. For his firſt begotten ſonne Cayne that Parriſide, bathing his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds in his brothers blood, did abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly declare the calamitie of nature corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the crueltie of ſinne, blindnes bred naturally in his breſt, the prauitie of his vvill, and wickednes of his hart.</p>
            <p>Almightie god him ſelfe lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth this<note place="margin">God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth mans fall.</note> ſoule fall of man in Paradiſe, &amp; appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth condigne puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for the ſame: and therwithall proteſteth that himſelfe was not the author of this corruption of creatures, whiche was created by him, in his ſonne, in iuſtice &amp; holynes of truth: wherin he taught mankinde that ſinne and all the effects therof had his origin of the diuell, and of man: as it is written,<note place="margin">Gene. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>It irketh me that euer I made man.</hi> Agayne,
<pb facs="tcp:20974:22"/> 
               <hi>He that committeth ſinne, is of the Diuell. For the diuell ſinned from the beginning.</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, <hi>By one man ſinne entered into the worlde, and through ſinne death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now albeit man receyued ſo greeuous a wound in his body and minde, vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvith not onely the image of god in him vvas defiled and deſtroyed, but alſo his povvers and ornamentes euerye vvaye vvere maruelouſly decayed: beſides the remouing of immortalitie, whereof by worde &amp; ſacrament god aſſured him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his tranſgreſsion: and in place therof a ſubiection to ſickneſſes &amp; death it ſelfe. Yet the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d death did not out of hand<note place="margin">The ſecond death came not by and by after mans fall.</note> ſeaſe vpon Adam, but God left him like a Pylgreme or baniſhed man out of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe many yeeres, in this animall or corporall lyfe, after the acte and decree was publiſhed, that god of his immence and infinite mercy woulde repayre his Image blotted &amp; defaced: and his good pleaſure was, that man paſsing his time,<note place="margin">Man lefte as a pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grime or exiled man vpon the earth.</note> &amp; running his race prefixed here in this vvorld, ſhould in his body (whiche vvas made ſo ſubiect and ſeruile vnto ſinne) be reſolued into duſt and earth: but in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20974:22"/> ſoule he appoynted him to be immortal, becauſe the ſame was breathed into him by god: whiche he alſo ordeyned to be a daily teſtimonie &amp; reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance vnto ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſwel of his eſtate before his fall, as of his glorification after the day of iudgement.</p>
            <p>Which bodily death al the children of<note place="margin">All the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſubiect to death.</note> Adam are ſubiect vnto, by meanes of ſinne abounding, yea and raigning in them, beeing nothing but duſt poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which muſt returne into duſt: after which the ſecond death, to wit, eternall condemnation both of body and ſoule, followeth, and is aſſuredly to be looked for of all thoſe that doo contemne the ſonne of God, mans mediator and aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate: and doo not ſeeke to bee deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from Gods wrath and indignation by the effuſion of hys moſte precious blood, vvhiche onely is able to purifie and vvaſhe men cleane from all their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>And to thende that this great ruine<note place="margin">A do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eful &amp; lamentable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of mans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by certayne auncient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> and decay of man after hys fall maye bee more euidently perceyued, I vvyll put dovvne the lamentable complayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of diuers Writers concerning this
<pb facs="tcp:20974:23"/> matter, vvhereby at the firſte vevve the matter will moſte playnely appeare and ſhewe it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And firſt, that is a notable &amp; memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble<note place="margin">Aug. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Iulianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. li. 4. cap. 14. repetit ex lib. 3. Cic. de repub.</note> ſaying of Cicero, repeted by S. Augu. touching the corruption of mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>Man is brought foorth, and as it vvere expelled into this world by nature, beeing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his ſtepdame then a louing mother. In bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy naked, frayle, and infyrme: and in minde, carefull in ſorowes, abaſhed in feare, vveake in labors, prone to pleaſure, hauing in him notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding certayne ſparkes and ſeedes of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature.</hi> Wherin as ſainct Auguſtine ſayth, he rightly deplored and bevvay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led our miſerable and pitifull caſe, and ſavve the horrible euent: Yet vvas he ignoraunt of the cauſe, neither dyd he perceyue that a heauy yoke vvas layde vpon all the children of Adam, from the time of their byrth vntill their death, by meanes of originall ſinne, wherwith they are infected and corrupted.</p>
            <p>Sainct Auguſtine him ſelfe writeth<note place="margin">De Ciuita. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> dei. lib<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 22. ca. 22</note> after this manner: <hi>I doo omitte howe God created Man righte: But touching our diſcente from our firste Parentes, that wee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20974:23"/> are thereby a generation forlorne, and caste a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, this very life of ours (if it be to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a life vvhich is ſo full of deadly miſeries) doth moſte playne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y declare. For what other thing can vve gather of that horrible and depe ignoraunce (vvhereof all Error proceedeth) vvhich poſſeſſeth and deteyneth the children of Adam in profounde darknes ſo violently, that a man can not ridde him ſelfe thereof vvithout great labar, ſorrowe, and feare? What other thing doth that loue of vayne and deceitfull things import, and therwithall ſuch conſuming cares, perturbations, ſorrowes, feares, diſceitfull ioyes, diſcordes, adulteries, fornications, incests, rapes, and vncleane commixtions agaynst na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, vvhich may not bee vvell named: and therewithall hereſies, blasphemies, periuries, oppreſſions of Innocentes, ſlaunders, falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, vniust iudgements, and other ſuche like miſcheefes, vvhich we ſee incident to mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</hi> And to conclude, as Viues writing in the ſame place ſayth: <hi>There vvoulde</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ludouicus Viues in 22 Auguſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de Ciui. ca. 22</note> 
               <hi>be founde no beast more ſauage and vnbrideled then man, if he vvere not chastiſed and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vvith diſcipline and good education: for if he might runne his owne race, he would conuert all his force and power to ſatisfie his
<pb facs="tcp:20974:24"/> filthy lustes and appetites: neither vvere it poſſible to finde any brute beastes more fierce and vvylde then manne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſainct Barnarde writeth very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly<note place="margin">Barnar. in ſermone 1. paruorum ſermonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> of this matter in this ſorte: <hi>That bleſſed and eternall Trinitie, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghost, one God of cheefe power, wiſedome, and goodnes, did create ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trinitie after his image and ſimilitude, vvhiche had certayne reſembla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nces of that eternall Trinitie: I meane the reaſonable Soule vvhiche conſisteth of Reaſon, memorie, &amp; vvill. And he created the ſame in ſuch ſort, that by participation of him he might be bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: and beeing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erted from him, ſhoulde be most miſerable. And this created Trinitie did rather bende it ſelfe to followe the motion of his owne vvill, then to ſtande in that liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vvhiche vvas giuen vnto it. And therfore it ſell through ſuggeſtion, delectation, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that fayre &amp; beautifull trinitie, that is to ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> power, wiſdome, &amp; puritie, into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie and filthy trinitie: verily into infirmitie, bundneſſe, and vnclenneſſe. For Memorie is become impotent and infirme, Reaſon improui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and darke, and the vvill impure. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er Memorie falling as it were vpon harde
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20974:24"/> Rockes, was broken and rent into three partes, namely into affectionate, heauie, and idle cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. I call thoſe affections, vvherewithall man is encombred about cares of things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, as in eating, drinking, and ſuche like. And thoſe are to be accompted heauy, vvhich we ſpende about the exerciſe of externall and harde buſines. And thoſe are vayne and feeble vvherewith mans minde is neyther affected nor greatly molested, and yet notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is drawen from the contemplation of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly thinges: as to ſpende his time in behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding how byrdes doo flye, or dogges doo runne. The light of Reaſon alſo hath three manner of vvayes fallen into ruine. For vvhereas it vvas his propertie to diſcerne betweene good and euill, truth and falſhood, profite &amp; diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite: It is nowe couered with ſuch darknes, that it is caried most co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly into a peruers iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, receyuing euill for good, falſhood for truth, inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie for commoditie. Wherein it coulde neuer haue erred ſo miſerably, if it had not bene depriued of that light which it had in the firſt creation. Whereby it is nowe commen to paſſe, that man hath lefte that vſuall and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie instrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to vnderſtand wiſdome, that is to ſay, Ethicke, Logike, &amp;, Phiſike: which we
<pb facs="tcp:20974:25"/> may otherwiſe call the ſcience Morall, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatiue, and Naturall. For by Ethicke good thinges are elected, and euill thinges re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed: by Logicke vve diſcerne truth from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth: by Phiſicke vve distinguiſhe betweene thinges profitable and vnprofitable. After this followeth mans vvill, vvhiche hathe had a triple ruyne. For vvhereas it vvas the propertie of vvill to cleaue faste to vertue and Innocencie, and entierly to loue the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme maiestie: through ſelfewill and pryde it is fallen from heauen to earth, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough concupiſcence of the eyes, luste of the fleſhe, and pride of lyfe, dothe nowe loue and embrace vvorldly thinges. Nowe vvhat can bee more vnhappie then this fall and ruine of mannes estate, vvhereby his memorie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> reaſon, and vvill, are ſo pitifully em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payred, and vvhole man ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably corrupted?</hi> (▿)</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:20974:25"/>
            <head>¶ The third part of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomie, ſhewing the remnants of <hi>Gods Image in man after his fall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>ECAVSE THE CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration<note place="margin">what is re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyned in mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of gods image</note> of contraries doe moſte plainely explicate all thinges, therefore I vvill as briefely as I can shevv by col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of <hi>Antitheſes,</hi> vvhat is reteyned in mans nature of the image of God: For that vve haue ſuſteyned a great loſſe, and an horrible ſhipwracke of heauenly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duments &amp; qualities, it hath bene plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and euidently declared. As for the<note place="margin">The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles &amp; Eth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicks are ignorant of the fall of man.</note> Ethnicks and Gentiles, they are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant of Adams tranſgreſſion, and doe ſuppoſe that throughe malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous nature, mankinde hath bene ſubiect to thraldome and miſeries, euen from the beginning.</p>
            <p>Man hath loſt that excellent vviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knovvledge vvhich he had in diuine and ſpirituall matters: Eſpecially<note place="margin">what know ledge remai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth in man touching y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> firſt table.</note> touching the eſſence and vvorshipping of God, properly apperteyning to the firſt table. And hath left in him onely
<pb facs="tcp:20974:26"/> certen ſparkes and ſeedes of the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his hart, to wit, <hi>That there is a God, &amp; that he is to be worſhipped: that he is a ſincere and iuſt power, rewarding vertue, &amp; puniſhing vice.</hi> Whiche knowledge although it be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure: yet is it a pricke or ſtinge in the conſcience, vexing the hart in heynous offences, and breeding terrible terrors of Gods wrath &amp; indignation: Hereof ariſe thoſe notable ſentences of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience in the wrytinges of the Heathen. This ſmal knowledge is maruelous obſcure in man forlorne, &amp; is oftentimes euen bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and vtterly blotted out by mans wilfull obſtinacie: whereof the Phalmiſt ſpeaketh, <hi>The fooliſh body hath ſayde in his hart, there is no God.</hi> And againe: <hi>All his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations are that there is no God, God doth not ſee it.</hi> Muche like to the Cyclops, wherof the Poet maketh mention: <hi>I force not for the threates of the Goddes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man hath alſo almoſte loſte perfecte<note place="margin">what kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wledge he hath lefte vnto him in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond table.</note> wiſdome in the ſeconde table, that is to ſay, of mundayne &amp; worldly things: But he hath left vnto him a certen wiſdome in externall accions and vertues apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining to the ſecond table, that is to ſay,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20974:26"/> 
               <hi>a power to diſcerne betweene things honest and vnhonest,</hi> and to vnderſtand the grounds of liberall artes, of good lawes, &amp; of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt accions. This knowledge of reaſon, as the Philoſophers call it, was not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extinct in mans ruyne. For it vvas Gods good pleaſure, that there ſhoulde yet be ſome difference betweene reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable man and brute beaſtes. And ſurely they differ in nothing ſo much as by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betweene ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; brute beaſtes.</note> that light vvhich yet in ſome ſort thineth in mans hart, conteining a certen rule or paterne of all artes and accions. And although the Pſalmiſt ſeemeth to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> take away this difference, <hi>Man beeing in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 49.</note> 
               <hi>honor, indured not, but became like the beaſtes of the fielde:</hi> yet wee muſte call to minde that ſimilitudes doo holde but in ſome reſpecte. For in this place man is compared to bruite Beaſtes, becauſe he is no leſſe ſubiect to death then they bee: Euen as Sainct Auguſtine do the<note place="margin">Auguſt. de peccat. ori. contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> vvell expounde it, ſaying, he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared in corruption, and not in vvhole nature vnto brute beaſts. This remna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of vviſdome &amp; knowlege, albeit vnperfect, is called the <hi>lawe of nature,</hi> or <hi>naturall lawe:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20974:27"/> and is ſet out by ſaint Paule, with excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 2.</note> termes and ſpeeches, <hi>as that it is the doctrine of God, &amp; the worke of the law writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in mans hart.</hi> Hereof commeth the knowledge of manuarie and liberall ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, ſo needefull for mans life: hence all ciuill lavves haue their origen, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with diſcipline &amp; ſocietie betwene man and man, the deſire of praiſe, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyding of diſpraiſe, the honor of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and the puniſhment of vices.</p>
            <p>That knowledge which was ſo notable<note place="margin">Mannes knowledge in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of things alto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether loſt.</note> in our firſt parentes, touching the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of thinges, is altogether loſte, and what ſo euer we haue, we haue it by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation and experience. For our eyes do behold the courſe of the planets: and reaſon deuiſeth inſtruments to take the altitude, longitude, and latitude of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Againe with our eyes vve looke vppon herbes: but reaſon ſearcheth oute the ſtrength, vſe, &amp; application: And ſo with our ſenſes vve comprehende liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: But mans induſtrie by vſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, vnderſtandeth their proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties<note place="margin">Adam be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his fall an excellent Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher.</note> and natures. But Adam before his fall, was an excellent Diuine, an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20974:27"/> Lawyer, and an excellent Philoſopher.<note place="margin">Man hath loſte all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; ſoule.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Man hath alſo vtterly loſt all ſanctity, iuſtice, and purity, both of body and of ſoule, by meanes of that filthy plague or leproſie, which hath inuaded and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted all our ſubſtance: ſo that Iob cryed out not without cauſe, <hi>Who can make him cleane, that is borne of vncleane.</hi> And ſaint<note place="margin">Iob. 14. Reg. 3.</note> Paul, <hi>All men haue ſinned:</hi> And there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth but novv in him a certen car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall appetition of iuſtice, comming from the lavve of nature and precepts of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. This is only an externall diſcipline or honeſty of lyfe, which is very weake and faint, as we al by experience are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to confeſſe: For novve the malice of<note place="margin">What in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks haue.</note> our nature doth wonderfully preuaile, and hindereth good diuices and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours: Wherefore in all places of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vvhere vve finde iuſtice attributed vnto the Gentiles: We muſt vnderſtand thereby externall iuſtice, or the iuſtice of the fleſhe. Man hath loſt that fre facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<note place="margin">Mans po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges loſt. 1. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and power of his ſtrength &amp; mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in theſe things, which are ſpirituall and appertayne to the true worſhipping of God. And beſides that, his powers or
<pb facs="tcp:20974:28"/> facultie eyther to deſire, or to deteſte thinges carnall and earthly, is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully impaired, vexed, and troubled, yea and oftentimes peruerſe. As Medea rightly ſaide,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Video meliora, probo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, deteriora ſequor.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Medaea.</note>
            </p>
            <p>He hath yet left vnto him ſome vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding<note place="margin">Man hath yet left ſom vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in worldly things.</note> in worldly things ſubiect to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. For if man were without this alſo, he ſhould then differ nothing at al fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brute beaſts: and without this no diſcipline, no iudgement, nor no puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t could be exerciſed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the Infidels. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth that diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betwene things that worke woluntarily &amp; naturally: and in like maner betvveene things wrought reaſonably and brutishly.</p>
            <p>In that therfore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſomtime co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſulteth<note place="margin">All mans vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in worldly things is a portion of gods image yet remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</note> and determineth happily in ciuill &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal things, it is a portion of the image of God: although moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly cernal affections, &amp; leude perturbations of the mind, do carie reaſon &amp; wil, quite out of the right way. But yet thoſe powers of man, hovve feeble or faynt ſoeuer they be, whether they be of the minde, of the vvill, of the hart, or of any other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20974:28"/> of man, if they bee good affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they are certayne remnauntes of Gods image.</p>
            <p>Man hath alſo almoſt loſt that notable<note place="margin">Mans po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minia oncr liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures much impayred.</note> wiſdome, and abſolute authoritie of rule and dominion ouer liuing creatures: For albeit there remayneth in him vnto this day ſome povver ouer them, yet the ſame is ioyned vvith greate perill and greefe, not vvanting tyrannie and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie. For the horſe vvyll not obey man vvithoute bytte and brydle: neyther vvyll the Oxe dravve the Plough vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out he bee yoked. The ſheepe will not yeelde wooll and milke, vnleſſe ſhe be bounde: Byrdes are taken vvith polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and cunning: And fishes vvith the hooke, net, &amp; other inſtrumentes. As for Tygres, Lyons, Beares, Woolfes, Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſuche like, they are not onely not obedient, but extreme aduerſaries to mankinde.</p>
            <p>Nowe if any man aske vvhye God made vvilde beaſtes ſo diſobedient and hurtful to man? It is to be anſwered, that this is commen to paſſe, <hi>That diſobedient children might be corrected.</hi> For man vvell
<pb facs="tcp:20974:29"/> deſerued ſuche a ſcourge after his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion: And therefore by meanes of ſinne, our ſeruants are armed againſt vs, &amp; wild beaſts ſuffred to torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; afflict vs: for ſo the ſcripture ſaith: <hi>I wil ſende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eze. 5.</note> 
               <hi>you famine and wilde beaſtes:</hi> When man was in the ſtate of innocency, they were all tame and obedient vnto him:<note place="margin">A duble co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity.</note> And novve thoughe they rebell, yet by Gods mercy, fewe doe periſhe by them: And if anye miſcarie, there ariſeth therof a double commodity: Firſt an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of gods ſeueritie, as in the Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes, who were killed of Lyons. In the<note place="margin">2. Reg. 17. 1. Reg. 13. 2. Reg. 2.</note> children that for ſcorning at Elizeus, were deſtroyed of Beares, and in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient prophet, who perished with the Lyon. Secondly gods maieſty herein, ſhevveth it ſelfe mightely, in that he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to cauſe the wilde and cruell beaſtes to reuenge his cauſe againſt diſobedient perſons. And finally herein we may alſo conſider gods great goodneſſe tovvarde vs, in ſecluding &amp; shutting them vp out of mennes ſocietie, into deſertes &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſes, appoynting them the night to walke in, and to ſeeke their pray, whiles
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20974:29"/> morning when man goeth about his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines, they all auoyd his ſight &amp; preſence, and lie hid in their dennes with trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and feare.</p>
            <p>Man hath alſo loſt eternall felicitie and<note place="margin">Man hath loſt eternall felicitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and bleſſedneſſe.</note> bleſſedneſſe, and hath onely lefte vnto him in ſteede thereof, this worldly and earthly lyfe: which is ſhort, miſerable, &amp; painefull, and is ſubiect to daungerous death euery moment. For cruell death<note place="margin">Death the poſſeſſor of all men, and the cauſe therof.</note> ſeaſoneth vppon all men that are borne of corrupt parents, aſſone as they are fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioned in their mothers wombe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are infected with ſinne: And therfore all the dayes of their lyfe, death is (as it were) mans hangman and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Firſt the imbecillity of mans ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance<note place="margin">The ſting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of death.</note> and ſtrength, is the bitte of Satan: Then the shortnes of mans lyfe, the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils &amp; dangers in the ſame, the cruell di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, the vntimely, ſoden, &amp; vnnatural deathes, &amp; the reſolution of our bodies into duſt &amp; aſhes, do euidently expreſſe his force and malice againſt mankinde. Whiche thinges I willingly note, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monishe men deepely to conſider their miſerable and wretched eſtate. For man
<pb facs="tcp:20974:30"/> is not only a bubble of water, during but a ſhort time, &amp; ſodenly vanishing away: but he is a thing much more miſerable, wherby it is moſt apparant, that man is not now any longer the excellent image of God, but the bondſlaue of the diuell: then the whiche there can bee nothing more lamentable or miſerable.</p>
            <p>But the vſe of that which we haue vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red<note place="margin">The vſe of this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</note> alreadie touching the remnantes of Gods image in man, is to put vs in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thoſe great things which we haue loſt by ſinne, and thoſe rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants are much like the rubble of a faire and beautifull citie deſtroyed, And ſuch as they be they ought not to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: beeing as it were notes &amp; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunces that god will in eternall life re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new &amp; reſtore his image to man, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his holy worde. Prouided always that by meanes of this doctrine no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer at all be aſcribed to man in ſpirituall matters before regeneration, and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer much neither in carnall and earthly things. For both theſe exceſſes are cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable. Let vs therefore bewayle this great loſſe of ours; and agayne let vs not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20974:30"/> forget to geue thanks, that it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to leaue in vs ſome print of his image: and cheefly let vs reioyce that by Chriſte wee are regenerate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God in this life, and that his Image ſhall be perfectly reſtored vnto vs in the life to come.</p>
            <p>And before I conclude this parte,<note place="margin">Errors co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</note> I thinke it not amiſſe to admonishe my Reader of certayne deteſtable and groſſe Errors, quite contrarie to this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Firſt certayne Athiſtes and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures hold, that there is nothing corrupt in man, after his firſt creation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: vvhich opynion the Manichees doo alſo mayntayne. And this Error ſeemeth too ſpringe of meere Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of mannes creation and fall. The Pelagians and certayne Schole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men dreamed mannes nature to bee ſyncere and vncorrupte after hys Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie, euen as Adam vvas before his fall. But that furor is directly agaynſt the vvorde of God: <hi>Beholde I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> 
               <hi>in iniquitie.</hi> And agayne, <hi>The</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
               <hi>ſence of the fleſhe is Enimitie agaynste the ſpirite.</hi> And ſome alſo nowe a dayes
<pb facs="tcp:20974:31"/> vvrite that there is ſome povver in man<note place="margin">Synergiſtae</note> before regeneration, euen in ſpirituall thinges: and that man is a cooperator or worker vvith God, and that it is in mans power to take, to folow, to aſſent (albeit faintly) with God in ſpirituall thinges: which is meere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: for the Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>The naturall</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> 
               <hi>man perceiueth not thinges whiche be of Gods ſpirite, for they are foliſhneſse vnto him,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of man not regenerate.</p>
            <p>Finally this extremitie is to be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, that there is no porcion at all of gods image left in man. And that there is left vnto man no knovvledge of God at al, &amp; that he hath no principles of arts or accions: but that hee is muche like a cleane sheete of paper ot table, into the vvhiche vvith education and ſtudy, hee maye write thinges. But ſaint Paule ſaith: <hi>That the worke of the lawe is written in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> 
               <hi>the Gentiles hartes.</hi> And euen by the law of nature thoſe that be not yet regenerate, haue ſome knovvledge, albeit obſcure, that there is a God, and that he is a iuſte God. Albeit they vnderſtande nothing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20974:31"/> of his eſſence, and of his perfect wil, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in the lavve and goſpell.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <head>The fourth part of the Anatomie of the renouation, <hi>or regeneration of the olde Man.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VT OF WHAT EXCEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent dignitie and honor, man vvas depoſed and caſte, by meanes of his tranſgreſſion, and vtterly drovvned in a deepe ſea of all euill, it hath bene already briefely and plainely declared: It now remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that vve haue ſome due conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Gods greate mercy, povver,<note place="margin">Gods migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty mercy.</note> and goodneſſe in the renouation, and regeneration of the olde manne. For after the fall of Adam, God could not doe any thing eyther more mightely or mercifully, then to ſende his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne to take our nature vppon him, to vvashe vs from our ſinnes vvith his precious blood, and to redeeme and deliuer vs from Satan. For this ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:20974:32"/> benefite, let vs continually vppon our knees geue moſte hartie and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt thankes vnto oure God euer and euer.</p>
            <p>And although this great vvorke of<note place="margin">Ethnickes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation.</note> God, with many other things ſpirituall, ſeeme ridiculous to the carnall man, and humaine ſence: and prophane Nations accompt it but a deuiſe of phanaticall perſons, yet all thoſe that are vnder the Inſigne of Chriſt, ought tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfully to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, &amp; highly to eſteme this hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome worke &amp; benefite of God: This do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine iſſueth out of the places of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, of Iuſtification, and of Baptiſme. For Regeneration conioyneth and lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all theſe thinges together.</p>
            <p>Regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſignifieth not in this place<note place="margin">The ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the worde regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> to returne corporally into our mothe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rs womb, &amp; to be borne againe, as Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ſuppoſed, but a ſpiritual renewing: and the ſimilitude is taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall natiuitie. For as man is conceiued &amp; borne of his natural mother in ſinne: euen ſo in this ſpiritual natiuitie, by the efficacie of gods worde and ſacramentes, externall inſtrumentes, he is regenerate
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20974:32"/> and ſpiritually made cleane from ſinne, that is to ſay, he receyueth remiſsion of ſinnes, he is made the ſonne of God, the temple of the holy ghoſt, and an heire of eternall life, albeit the ſpottes of Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall<note place="margin">Ioh. 1. &amp;. 3 Tit. 3. 1. Pet. 1. 2.</note> ſinne doo yet remayne in this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of his. And vnder this generall worde Regeneration, mans conuerſion vnto God, his iuſtification, and the effectes thereof, are comprehended and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned.</p>
            <p>Regeneration of Chriſtians in Gods<note place="margin">The defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation.</note> inuiſible accion, plainly expreſſed by his holy worde and ſacramentes annexed vnto the ſame: whereby our mercifull God doth ſpiritually forme and faſhion of a carnall man, a newe, iuſt, and holy manne, ingraffing him into his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, remouing from hym his ſinnes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, his wrath &amp; indignation, and imparteth vnto him his iuſtice &amp; grace: deliuereth him alſo from the power and kingdome of the Diuell, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him the holye ghoſt, the earneſt pledge of eternall lyfe: and fynallye kindleth in him newe ſtrength to begin newnes of life, acceptable and pleaſaunt
<pb facs="tcp:20974:33"/> vnto God in this world. The groundes this definition are the words of the holy ſcripture: <hi>Go teach all nations, baptiſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar. 16. Iohn. 3. Tit. 3.</note> 
               <hi>in the name of the father, the ſonne, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghost: and he that beleeueth and is bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſhall bee ſaued.</hi> This Renouation, as I ſayde before, is a matter of the greateſt moment, and an eſpeciall ſigne of Gods loue and mercy toward man. For when godleſſe man put vpon him the image of the diuell, and was therby more then op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with many miſeries, and had caſt away al hope of releefe: the louing Lord vſed a wonderfull temperature of iuſtice and mercy, and miniſtred medicines to man, his ſonne euen then beeing a Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciter and interceſſor for vs.</p>
            <p>This ſonne of the eternall father our<note place="margin">The work of regenera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning.</note> Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, was from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning appoynted to deſcend &amp; take mans nature vpon him, and was ſubiect to all humaine infirmities, ſinne excepted. He appeared to deſtroy the works of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, to ſeeke the loſt grote, wherin Gods image vvas ſtamped, to bring home the loſt ſheepe to the folde of eternall life, to thende that he might florishe for euer
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20974:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> there vvith al heauenly companies, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here regenerated, and there accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods image perfectly renevved. For when man kinde had receiued moſt greeuous vvoundes, and vvas bounde in ſtrong chaynes, not able to be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by mans ſtrength: this bruſer of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentes head, came &amp; profeſſed him ſelfe (when the fulneſſe of time ſhould come) to be our tender and faythfull Phiſition, to geue his fleſh for the life of the world; and that he woulde ſuffer ſuche puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that by his ſtripes and vvoundes we ſhould be healed: and that through death he ſhoulde be deſtroyed that had povver of death, to vvit, the diuell, that craftie ſerpent &amp; cruell dragen, the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of man from the beginning.</p>
            <p>This regeneration of mankinde vvas<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man by Ieſus Chriſt.</note> then done by none other but by Ieſus Chriſt, our Prieſt, and euerlaſting king: who collecteth &amp; preſerueth his church by the ſound of his Goſpell, vvherein is written the decree of our reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliation: Which Goſpell (he beeing the eternall worde of the eternall father) reueleth vnto vs: Shevving the chearefull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb facs="tcp:20974:34"/> of his father, and powring the holy ghoſt into our harts, that with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect loue and heauenly ioy, we might in obedience be vnited to our God. Which propertie of his office, &amp; ſpeciall priuile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, he hath made moſt manifeſt by his reſurrection, &amp; by the ſending downe of the holy ghoſt vpon the Apoſtles, that thereby vve might the better conſider the ineſtimable price of that benefite. The ſonne of God, together with the<note place="margin">Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce.</note> Prophets &amp; Apoſtles, do exhort vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, that we might be renued and clothed with that newe image, and rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate to a celeſtiall wiſdome &amp; iuſtice. And to thende that we might know the deformitie of the olde Adam: and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to ſeeke gods image in Chriſt, who is the newe and heauenly Adam, we muſt vſe both the lavve and the Goſpell. The Lavve (I ſaye) that vvee ſtricken vvith feare and dread in reſpect of our ſinnes, might be enforced to ſeke after the true and perfect Phiſition, who is Chriſt, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Goſpell affyrmeth to be made vnto vs, vviſedome, redemption, iuſtice, and ſanctification.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:20974:34"/>
            <p>But wee muſte alſo vnderſtande, that<note place="margin">what kinde of iuſtice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s reſtored in regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> not onely that iuſtice which was gotten by Chriſtes blood, is transferred vnto vs through gods wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull grace &amp; mercy: but in this regeneration there is a redeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie or reſtitution of certen powers or ſtrengthes in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, out of the which certen accions iſſue &amp; flowe. And yet this reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution is not ſo perfect, as that vve are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eyther to fulfill the Lawe, or to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted iuſt before God: but it is the fruite of Iuſtice Imputatiue (as they call it) albeit in ſome places &amp; other reſpect it haue the name of Iuſtice: as, <hi>That I</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> 
               <hi>may be founde in him not hauing mine owne iuſtice, which is of the lawe, but that whiche is of fayth in Christ.</hi> I vvill therfore write ſomvvhat particularly of the powers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to the godly in regeneration, and aftervvarde I will ſpeake of their accions and vvorkes.</p>
            <p>And firſt of al mans mind hath certen<note place="margin">Of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> minde renewed.</note> powers or habilities reſtored by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt, and a kinde of light kindled in thinges ſpirituall and diuine. <hi>Be yee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> (ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>in the ſpirite of your mindes.</hi> And, <hi>Renewe the newe man in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:20974:35"/> 
               <hi>the knowledge of God.</hi> And agayne: <hi>We all</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.</note> 
               <hi>vvith face reueled, beholding the glory of the Lodre, are transformed into the ſame image, from brightnes to brightnes, as it were by the ſpirite of the Lorde.</hi> There is then reſtored ſome power &amp; abilitie vnto mans mind, ſomewhat to vnderſtand the diuine and heauenly myſteries: and a certayne light to diſcerne the doctrine of God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rule of his worde, from falſe doctrine and hereſie. For it hath vſually come to paſſe in all ages, that Errors ſpringing vp, haue bene paynted vvith goodly colours, vvhereby manye haue bene ſeduſed and deceyued.</p>
            <p>But ignorance and blindneſſe bred in<note place="margin">Muche ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and blindneſſe yet remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s minde.</note> man naturally, is not altogether remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued out of his minde: The reaſon therof is, becauſe in this life mans reſtitution is not perfected, but attempted only: and the diſeaſe of originall ſinne remayneth after this ſpirituall Regeneration. The olde nature, or olde man remayneth, albeit ſome mortification be begon. For ſo the Apoſtle ſayth: <hi>We knowe in part, we</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.</note> 
               <hi>propheſie in part: but vvhen that vvhiche is perfect is come, that vvhich is vnperfect ſhal be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20974:35"/> done away.</hi> And heereof it commeth to paſſe, that ignorances of God and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall thinges (not knovven vnto vs by nature) do oftentimes exceedingly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comber and vnquiet euen the man rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate: So that lighte and darknes in mans minde, doo contende and ſtriue one with another, as the Apoſtle moſte grauely teacheth in theſe vvordes: <hi>The</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> 
               <hi>fleſhe coueteth agaynst the ſpirite, and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite agaynſt the fleſhe: theſe are contrarie one to another.</hi> And nowe and then the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance &amp; darknes of the minde doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the ſmall light kindled, eyther vvith groſſe ſecuritie, or curious philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, or carnall reaſon, as vve knowe it came to paſſe in Aaron, Salomon, and Hieroboam, vvho vvilfully ſhooke of this diuine light: and gaue them ſelues to the vvorshipping of Idols.</p>
            <p>Let vs not maruell therfore, that there is yet remayning ſuche great imbecilitie in thoſe that be regenerate: neither yet becauſe ſome excellent men, accompted<note place="margin">why excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent lightes of Chriſtes Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all.</note> lightes of the Church, doo often times erre &amp; fall very groſſely, ſeeing the cauſe thereof is ſo apparant: to vvitte, firſt the
<pb facs="tcp:20974:36"/> ſicknes of originall ſinne remayning yet in the poſteritie of Adam: and ſecondly, the craft, furor, and power of the diuell, vvho vvithout gods eſpeciall &amp; vvo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full grace is able to doo muche agaynſt ſeely and vveake man.</p>
            <p>As the minde hath receyued certayne<note place="margin">Of the will renued af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> ſeedes or nouriſhments of regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this life by gods grace: euen ſo vvill is partaker of ſome povver and abilitie to apprehende diuine and ſpiritual things, to couet after them, &amp; aſſent vnto them: which promptnes &amp; facultie it had not before regeneration, as the Apoſtle moſt excellently vvriteth after this maner: <hi>It</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> 
               <hi>is God that worketh in vs the vvill and the deede, according to his good will.</hi> And elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where he freely confeſſeth that he hath<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> will in diuine thinges, and as a ſpirituall man to be delighted with gods law. But yet the vvill is not perfectly reſtored in this life. For the filth &amp; dregges of ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſinne (albeit they are forgiuen by Chriſte) are yet abyding in vs, and can not wholly bee rooted out of this our Nature: Firſt therefore let vs conſider the vveakenes of Will, euen in thoſe that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20974:36"/> be regenerate, vvithout Gods ſpeciall and peculiar aſsiſtance, as vve ſee dayly in the confeſsions, afflictions, and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes<note place="margin">The weak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of the godly in the houre of death, and the cauſe thereof.</note> of the godly. Secondly, our vvyll is by our ovvne malice, and the ſubtiltie of Sathan, bothe letted, deformed, and ouercommen. Whiche imbecilitie and vveakenes, ſo deepely and daungerou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly faſtened vnto vs, the godly doo both taſte and feele, and alſo bevvayle and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: praying ſtill vvith earneſt gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that they may bee ridde oute of this thraldome, into bliſſe and peace euerlaſting. The voyce of the Apoſtle is vvorthy to bee hearde, which ſayth: <hi>Wyll is ready vnto mee, but I am not able</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> 
               <hi>to doo it. For I doo not that good thinge vvhiche I vvoulde doo, but that euill which I vvould not, that I doo. If I doo that which I vvoulde not, it is not nowe I, but ſinne dwelling in mee.</hi> And a little after: <hi>I ſee annother Lawe in my members, reſisting the lawe of my Minde, and leading mee captiue vnder the lawe of ſinne, vvhiche is in my members. O vnhappie man that I am, who ſhall deliuer mee from the body of this death? I geue God thankes throughe Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:20974:37"/> Christe our Lorde. Therefore in my minde I ſerue the lawe of God, but in my fleſhe the lawe of ſinne.</hi> In the vvhich vvords the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle affyrmeth, that he had a good will ſtirred vp by the holy ghoſt: But he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that the old Adam ſticking in him, did alwayes plucke him avvay to ſinne and wickednes. He further ſhevveth the author of regeneration in this life, and the perfecter therof in the life to come: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus Chriſt our ſauiour &amp; redemer.</p>
            <p>And yet God hath vvith his ſpirite of ſtrength and fortitude aſsiſted many thouſandes of his martyres, in giuing te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie<note place="margin">The princi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pal cauſe of the patience and ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of martyrs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſſions.</note> to the truth vvith vvonderfull patience and boldneſſe: vvhiche is the proper and peculiar worke of the holy ghoſt, vvho is thereof called a Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And that voice of the Apoſtle is moſt ſweete and delectable: <hi>God is faythfull, who</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> 
               <hi>vvill not ſuffer you to be tempted aboue that ye are able to beare: but in the middle of your temptation he will prouide that you ſhallbe able to beare it.</hi> God is always preſent with his ſeruants in their agonies, and doth moſt gratiouſly and plentifully giue them co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage &amp; ſtrength in cruell torments, that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20974:37"/> they become victors and conquerors.</p>
            <p>In thinges externall conioyned vvith<note place="margin">The pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of will regenerate in temporal thinges.</note> vertue and honeſty, mannes will after regeneration is vvithout all doubt more pliable then it was before. For the man regenerate hath the light of Gods word ſhining in his minde, wherby he percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and embraceth more readily both things diuine and humaine. It is a great vertue in Scipio, that hee conteyneth him ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Endibilis: But it was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out<note place="margin">What men not regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat cheefly reſpect in their acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> the light of the liuing god, his vvyll vvas therefore vntovvarde in ſpirituall thinges, he was an idolator, and in his accions onely reſpected externall hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, that hee might not doe any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt comelynes. But in Ioſeph refuſing vnlawfull company with his maiſters<note place="margin">Ioſeph his accions and the ground thereof.</note> wife, there ſhineth a more excellent and diuine vertue. For he had the knowledge of the lyuing god, and a vvil regenerate, whereby hee did more commodiouſly<note place="margin">A great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diuerſity of mans wyll both in tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe that be regenerate and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate.</note> practiſe things externall, he had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt his guide and leader, hee feared God, and was loth to deface his honor &amp; glory, hee aſſuredly beleeued that God vvould be with him and comfort him in
<pb facs="tcp:20974:38"/> perilles and daungers.</p>
            <p>There is alſo a greate difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thoſe that be not regenerate in thinges external, for one excelleth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in vertue, in diſcipline, &amp; in exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Moreouer there is often tymes ſeene great imbecilitie in the godly, vvho doe horribly deforme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in externall vices: the cauſe is the ſinne yet remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in their nature, which is no ſmal or light euill: Wherevnto the diuill addeth his poyſon and malice, eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the godly. Whereby it commeth to paſſe that no man (Chriſte excepted) be he neuer ſo learned or godly, is pure<note place="margin">The ſpots in the godly</note> and cleane from foule ſpottes and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences. And hereof come ſo many offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and faults of the beſt &amp; moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent men in the church of God in their externall accions, as Loth, vvho defiled<note place="margin">Loth. Dauid. Hely.</note> him ſelfe with dronkenneſſe and inceſt: Dauid with adultery and murder. Hely with negligence in the education of his children, &amp;c. So that many are choked, &amp;<note place="margin">The thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thys world.</note> oppreſſed with the thornes of this world, and very fewe ridde them ſelues oute of the ſame. All godly men ought to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20974:38"/> this their great infirmitie, and to pray continually, that God of his mercy woulde vouchſafe to gouerne our pathes and ſteppes in this ſlippery way of the worlde, that eyther we may not fall at all into foule offences, or at the leaſt that we may not be drowned, &amp; vtterly perish in the ſame.</p>
            <p>The newnes of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hart regenerat, is al<note place="margin">Of the hart of man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate.</note> ſo ſuch, that ſome diuine motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are ligh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tened (and as it were) kyndled: So there beginneth both a certen harmony of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in the harte, and alſo a certaine conſent of the mynde, will, and harte. And ſo it conceyueth by the ayde of the holy ghoſte (and not of it ſelfe), ſome ſparkes and ſeedes of a reuerende and childish feare of god, a loue of God and godly thinges, a wonderfull tollerancy and patience in afflictions, and a loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome deteſtation of ſinne and vvicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. It beginneth to reſtraine &amp; brydle raging affections, and embraceth hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auen Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with loue and charity. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit not ſo perfectly as the lawe requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.<note place="margin">Perfect na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture onely perfectly fulfilleth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lawe.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy god with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all thy harte, &amp; thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.</hi> For
<pb facs="tcp:20974:39"/> the perfect &amp; exact fulfilling of the law, belongeth to perfect &amp; incorrupt nature.</p>
            <p>There remayneth therfore in the harts of men regenerate, not onely a greate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie,<note place="margin">Greate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmityes remayne in mans hart after rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</note> coldnes, &amp; dulneſſe to all good motions: but the ſame motions are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded &amp; tumbled together as it were with a certaine whyrlewind. And moſte commonly corrupt affections beare rule, and burſt out with great ſhame and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie, as flames of luſt, deſire of reuenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, malice &amp; hatred, either too much or prepoſterous feare, or loue of exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and temporall thinges: And many in theſe ſtormes and tempeſts, are vtterly<note place="margin">The effects of raging affections.</note> caſte oute of Chriſtes shippe: and other ſome with muche adoe aryue in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in a bote all to rent and torne, as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in all ages maketh manifeſt. The hart therefore is muche lyke a ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſea of furious affections, ſubiect to<note place="margin">The harte is muche lyke a trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled ſea of raging af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</note> diuerſe ſtormes and tempeſtes, which if it be not made calme and quiet with the holy ghoſte: it will make greater ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackes in ſinne, then ſaylers do in Scyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la and Charibdis. The fountaine &amp; ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of theſe ſtormes &amp; tempeſtes is ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20974:39"/> ſin (as I haue often already repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) ſo deepely rooted in oure nature: Which the foule feend with his craft, fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and power ouer miſerable men, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelouſly augmenteth and increaſeth. And therefore Dauid beeing regenerate prayeth after this maner: <hi>Create in me, O God, a cleane harte, and renewe a right ſpirite within me.</hi> He felt, no doubt, in him ſelfe theſe raging fluddes of the hart, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall hee vvas toſt and almoſt oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed diuerſly, and with great daunger, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was he able to reſiſt the ſame with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute the ayde and aſſiſtance of the holy ghoſt.</p>
            <p>The man regenerate then by Gods<note place="margin">Of the good acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; work of men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate.</note> grace, beginneth nevv obedience, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and externall, whiche is acceptable to god through Ieſus Chriſt, who ſayeth vnto vs: <hi>I am the vine, &amp; you are the braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: he that abideth in me, and I in him, that man bringeth forth much fruite, for without me ye are able to doe nothing.</hi> When wee are therefore ingraffed in Chriſte by rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and made good, vve may doe good vvorkes, as the Apoſtle euidently declareth: <hi>We are his vvorkmanſhippe, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:20974:40"/> by Chriſt Ieſus in good workes, which God</hi>
               <note place="margin">The good workes of man regene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate, are vn perfect in this lyfe.</note> 
               <hi>hath prepared that we ſhould walke in.</hi> But we muſte alwayes remember that the good workes of men regenerate are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in this lyfe, according to the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the law, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God, with all thy hart, with all thy ſoule, &amp; with all thy ſtrength, and thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.</hi> And therefore man regenerate hath not remiſsion of ſinnes, and inheritance of eternall lyfe, by meanes of his ovvne iuſtice, which is vnperfect, but onely by<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of men regenerate.</note> iuſtice imputatiue, which is deriued vnto him by the iuſtice of Chriſte: yet the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regenerate hath this ſolace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that his newe obedience is accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and pleaſant vnto God: Becauſe he is reconciled to God by faith in Chriſt, and all his vvorkes, accions, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſpringeth of fayth. And moreouer almighty God of his greate and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant mercie, doth recompence and crovvne this nevve obedience, both in this lyfe and in the life to come.</p>
            <p>This punniſhment continueth all<note place="margin">Of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of man regene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate ouer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liuing creatures.</note> the dayes of mannes lyfe in this vvorlde, that the greate dignity, authoritie, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20974:40"/> rule, which our parentes had before the fall ouer other liuing creatures, is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored vnto him againe. The pleaſure of God is that ſome ſignes of our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and tranſgreſſion shoulde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvayes be obiect vnto our eyes: That we might the rather thereby feare and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his maieſtie. And yet we may alſo ſee Gods bleſſing, in making many bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes not onely tame, but alſo as it were familiar and domeſticall ſeruantes vnto vs: and that more willingly and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſlye they ſerue vs, then they ſerue the wicked and vngodly. And in lyke maner the fertilitie of the earth, is not<note place="margin">Of the frut fulnes of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> earth.</note> perfectly reſtored in this lyfe to man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate: and yet by the bleſsing of god all liuing creatures are fed, &amp; as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſaith, <hi>There is no ſcarſitie to thoſe that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 3. 4.</note> 
               <hi>feare him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There yet remaineth alſo in the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age<note place="margin">The mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of men regenerate.</note> of man regenerate, certen ſignes and admonitions of his tranſgreſſion, as in that childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are borne with paine &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril of their parent, &amp; are all by nature the ſons of wrath. And yet notwithſtanding God is preſent with his ſeruants in their<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:20974:41"/> mariages, and mitigateth the karkes &amp; cares thereof, but alſo conſerueth &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth peace, &amp; ſendeth ſome Halcions dayes: And often tymes for one good mans ſake, he bleſſeth whole regions and countries: as the examples of Ioſeph, Danyell, and many others, do ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare. The godly alſo haue this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue,<note place="margin">Ioſeph. Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell.</note> that becauſe they be true and lyuely members of Chriſtes church: they onely may aſſure them ſelues, that they bring forth ſeedes and plants of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Ieruſalem, and are as it were Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries bringing foorth (as Plato called<note place="margin">Plato.</note> them) worshippers of the diuine power and maieſtie</p>
            <p>The tyranny and furor of the diuyll<note place="margin">Of the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Deuil.</note> againſte menne Regenerate, ceaſſeth not in thys lyfe, becauſe ſinne remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth yet in oure nature. And Gods will alſo is that the enemie of mankinde shoulde bee perfectly knovven, that both the greate benefites of Chriſte, mighte more clearely ſhyne, and shevve them ſelues, and alſo that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cercyſe of fayth and confeſſion, might be more frequent and common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20974:41"/> his faythfull ſeruantes, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing children. For albeit the prince of this world be iudged already, and hys power and weapons made dull and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: yet he is not altogether remoued out of this vvorld, &amp; ſeparated from the Sainctes: for that ſhall not be abſolued and finiſhed before the laſt day.</p>
            <p>And becauſe mention hath oftentimes bene made of men regenerate, and not regenerate, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ende their differences may be more manyfeſt, I vvil put downe certayne Autithiſes, vvhereby the diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie<note place="margin">Autitheſes or certen differences betweene man rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and not rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate</note> betweene Alexander and Dauid, Plato and Paule, and other ſuche excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent wightes, vvill more manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. The Ethnickes haue onely a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall natiuitie: The Regenerate are borne of God ſpiritually. The Ethnickes want the true knovvledge of God, they doubt of his eſſence and will: although they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe excell in vviſdome, vertue, and good demerites: The Regenerate haue a ſure, certayne, and euident knowledge of God. The Ethnickes want all Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice imputatiue: The Regenerate are beautified vvith Chriſtes iuſtice, vvhiche
<pb facs="tcp:20974:42"/> he hath purchaſed with his blood. The Ethnickes haue onely the externall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of the ſeconde Table: The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate haue not onely the vvorkes of externall diſcipline, but the internall vvorkes of the firſte Table. The Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nickes dooing good vvorkes vvithout Chriſte, are not able too perſvvade them ſelues that their ſeruice plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God: ſeeing that ſaincte Paule ſayeth, What ſoeuer is not of fayth, is ſinne, and the vvorkes of the Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nickes proceedeth not of fayth: The Regenerate grounde their good vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes vppon fayth in Chriſte, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> certaynely knovve, that albeit the ſame bee vnperfecte in thys lyfe, yet that throughe Chriſte they are acceptable and pleaſaunt to God.</p>
            <p>The Ethnickes doo onely follovve the direction of their carnall Reaſon, and haue ſome little portion of the lavve of Nature: but they are altogether ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunte of thoſe thinges that bee of God: The Regenerate haue Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible vvoorde reueled by hys ſonne Chriſte. The Ethnickes can not call
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20974:42"/> vppon God, nor offer acceptable pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in their miſeries and calamities: The Regenerate are able to call vppon the liuing God, for they knovve that there is a God, vvhat he is, and that he is mercifull vnto them, throughe Chriſte, and that he vvyll geue vnto them bleſsinges ſpirituall and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. In their afflictions they knovve the fountayne of grace, they knovve the perfect remedie agaynſt ſinne, they knovve Gods promiſes, they referre the euent of thinges vnto God, and ſubmitte them ſelues vvhollye to hys good vvyll and pleaſure. The Ethnic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes can not haue firme and ſtable peace in their conſciences, vvhen they are in agonies and greefes, becauſe they are ignoraunt of God, of the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and of the vvoorde of promyſe: and therefore they are carryed into moſte abhominable and ſtinking ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of diſpayre: The Regenerate, beyng vexed vvith calamities, vvyth the lavve, and ſtynges of the Diuell in theyr conſciences: by meanes of
<pb facs="tcp:20974:43"/> Chriſte, vvho is their mediator and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour: they haue ſure &amp; certayne peace, they haue the vvorde of God, and the ſeales of the ſame, they haue the holy ghoſte, as an earneſt penie or pledge of their ſaluation. The Ethnickes after the Reſurrection, becauſe they beleeued not in Chriſt, ſhall be in hell vvythe the riche glotton: For Chriſte ſayth, <hi>They that beleene not ſhall not haue eternall life, but Gods wrath remayneth vpon them:</hi> The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate perſeuering in the true faith of Chriſt, ſhall be vvith God in ioy and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, hauing the fruition of Gods face and countenaunce, and the ſvveete ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie of all the bleſſed company in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, as the worde of God promiſeth.</p>
            <p>The Ethnickes therefore beeing moſte renowmed in vvorldly things, are much inferiour to the meaneſt man that is Regenerate.</p>
            <p>But ſome man vvill happily ſaye, if<note place="margin">Why the vertues &amp; noble actes of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles are eſteemed.</note> their vertues &amp; noble actes, their inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and explications of artes, their fluent and ſvveete eloquence, be of no more value: why doo men eſteeme them ſo muche? I anſvvere, that they doo it
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20974:43"/> but in degrees and reſpectes. And for that theſe woorkes are ſo excellent as mannes Reaſon can attayne vnto: they are ſo farre ſoorth to be alovved, as they agree vvith the lavve of nature, or true principles of thinges ingraffed in man naturally. Wherein vve ought to haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in remembraunce, that the Ethnickes haue receyued many thinges of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Gods Church, which they haue through their carnall vviſdome maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly corrupted. Moreouer, becauſe Artes, eloquence, and other ſuch things are needefull onely to this carnall life, vvee vſe them onely for the ſame. And as concerning Diuinitie, that is to ſay, the knowledge of diuine and heauenly thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, together with a true and perfect ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of good vvorkes, and examples of vertues, vvhiche vvere neuer to bee found in the Gentiles: vve deriue (I ſay) and dravve all theſe thinges out of the holy ſcripture. And thende vvhy theſe<note place="margin">The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of this doctrine.</note> diuerſities betweene Ethnickes &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are here recited by me, and vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be noted of others, are firſt, that vvee doo not aſcribe ouer muche to the
<pb facs="tcp:20974:44"/> Ethnickes, for their externall actes and deedes. Secondarily, that the excelencie and dignitie of man regenerate may be knowen. Thirdly, that vve might be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to giue god thankes for the ſame, &amp; to pray vnto him, that as he hath begon a good worke in vs, ſo he would conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue and perfite the ſame, vnto the daye of Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            <p>I might ſeeme to haue ſpoken ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently<note place="margin">Errors co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to this true doctrine.</note> of man regenerate: and ſo haue I in deede, but that certen olde and newe Errors in this matter are worthy the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimaduerſion, to thende that the godly and zelous Reader beeing admoniſhed, might the better bevvare and auoyde the ſame. The Papiſtes error is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie<note place="margin">The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes.</note> to the promiſe, which teacheth vs to doubt whether vvee be in the fayth, or not: whiche is a doctrine leading men into deſperation.</p>
            <p>The Saducees holde, that there is no<note place="margin">Saduces.</note> Regeneration, nor lyfe after thys.</p>
            <p>The Libertines alſo ſvvarue from this<note place="margin">Libertines</note> doctrine, holding that Regeneration is nothing but a libertie to follovve ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall luſtes and deſires. Contrarie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20974:44"/> that vveightie ſentence of Saincte Paule: <hi>Brethren, you are called into liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gala. 5.</note> 
               <hi>onely let not your libertie bee an occaſion to the fleſhe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Gnostickes, Catharickes,</hi> and ſome<note place="margin">Gnoſticks, Anabap. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Anabaptistes,</hi> are to bee noted alſo, who dreame, that men Regenerate, are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly iuſte in their nevvneſſe of lyfe in this vvoorlde. Whiche poſition is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectlye agaynſt the Scripture, and day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experience. For Chriſte doth teache vs to pray: <hi>Forgeue vs our trespaſſes.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation dothe not altogether take avvay the diſeaſe of ſinne, but the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, that it bee not layde to our charge.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="part">
            <head>The fyfth parte of the Anatomie, touching the eſtate <hi>of Man in his glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IF the fayth and hope of men Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, did extende no further then this preſent life, they were of all other creatures moſt miſerable. Their
<pb facs="tcp:20974:45"/> onely and cheefe comforte therefore is the certayne and aſſured expectation of conſummate glorye in the vvorlde to come. And although ſilence might ſeme more conueniente, then a fevve bare vvordes in ſo vveightie a matter: yet to thende that our hope may be the better comforted and ſtrengthened, and the heauenlye ioyes beeing apparantly ſet before our eyes, might be the more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueted and deſired on our partes, I vvyll alſo ſay ſomewhat of this matter. For<note place="margin">Thende of all thinges is at hande.</note> the time is euen at hande, when as all theſe vvorldly things, of vvhat moment ſoeuer they ſeeme to be, ſhall haue their ende: and the Regenerate perſeuering in a conſtant fayth, ſhall poſſeſſe ioy and endleſſe bliſſe. On thother ſide, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vngodly perſons, ſhall bee caſte downe into euerlaſting paynes and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. And this doctrine is ſetled vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon theſe groundes or places of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>Of the Gospell, of Iustification, of the rewardes of newe obedience, of the reſurrection, and of eternall life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The glorification of man in the life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, is Gods accion &amp; vvorke, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20974:45"/> hee reſtoreth vnto all beleeuers after their reſurrection his image perfectly, that is to ſaye, he will purifie and clenſe whole man, as well in body as in ſoule, from ſinne: And beautifying him with al integritie, wiſedome, &amp; iuſtice, will tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate him into his kingdome, to be a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe and companion of the angels and bleſſed ſpirites throughout all eternitie. For we learne by Gods vvord, that when the godly are remoued hence by corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral death, they lay aſide al their vveights and burdens of ſinne (which now ſo gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly preaſſeth them in this worlde, to the ende that man should not be mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted therewith after his reſurrection. For there is not onely a diſſolution of the body and ſoule but the dregges &amp; rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of ſinne, are alſo ſwallowed vp out of our nature: In ſo much that this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall death is an effectuall remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that puyſant and mighty enemy, which ſo dayly and violently aſſaulteth vs in this corruption &amp; mortality. When our bodies therfore are laid in the graue they reſte in ſure and certen hope of the glorious reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neither are they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned
<pb facs="tcp:20974:46"/> there to ignomie and shame, but<note place="margin">Of the qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lities &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties or glorified bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies. <hi>Ex Pet. Mart. in 2. Re. 4.</hi>
               </note> that they may riſe and ſpring vp againe with excellent properties and qualities: Whereof P. Martyr that excellent light of our tyme hath vvritten largely and learnedly, out of whome I vvill borrow ſo much as ſeemeth conuenient for this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The ſchoole me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſaith he) do call thoſe properties, conditions, or indumentes, neither can I miſlyke thoſe whiche they number, becauſe I ſee that they drawe them out of the holy ſcripture. Albeit I thinke they haue not collected all, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can any man doe that, becauſe vve cannot ſee or perceiue exactly in this life the heauenly glory of the celeſtiall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. But the firſt qualitie or indument<note place="margin">The firſte conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of glorified bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality.</note> accompted of them, is immortalitie. And in deed wherſoeuer any mention is made in the ſcripture of the lyfe to come, the ſame is ſaid to be eternall and euerlaſting. The Apoſtle ſayth: <hi>This mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> 
               <hi>muſt put on immortalitie, and this corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible muſt put on incorruption.</hi> And for that both rewardes and punishments which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20974:46"/> shall be geuen, according to the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of vvorkes, are eternall, the ſubiect or nature vvhich shall ſuſteyne the ſame, muſt needes be alſo eternall. Moreouer ſeeing Chriſte hath ouercome ſinne and death, it muſt of neceſſitie folovve, that the lyfe of holy menne shall be immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. The Apoſtle alſo ſpeaketh after this manner: <hi>Chriſt ryſing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deade, dieth not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> 
               <hi>any more, neither hath death power ouer him any more:</hi> And agayne, <hi>Fleſhe and blood ſhall</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> 
               <hi>not poſſeſse the kingdome of God:</hi> Whiche vvordes are not to be miſconſtrued of the very nature and ſubſtance of fleshe and blood: For thoſe that shall riſe to glorie, shall be clothed vvith them. But the Apoſtle meaneth of corruption, vvherevnto flesh and blood are ſubiect in this lyfe. And therefore it folovveth there: <hi>And this corruption ſhall put on in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this qualitie aryſeth another,<note place="margin">Glorified bodies need no ſuſtenta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral food.</note> vvhiche is that the glorified menne shall not neede meate, drinke, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye other corporall ſuſtentation in the lyfe to comme. Chriſte hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hathe taughte vs, that they
<pb facs="tcp:20974:47"/> shalbe lyke angels. For whereas mention is often tymes made in the ſcripture of eating and drinking in heauen, as: <hi>I will</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22.</note> 
               <hi>prepare for you, as my father hath prepared for me, a kingdome, that yee may eate and drinke vppon my table in my kingdome:</hi> This, and ſuche lyke ſpeeches are nothing els but metaphors or tranſlations, whereby the holy ghoſt admoniſheth rude and ſimple men of the ioyes and pleaſures of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lyfe. In the lyfe immortall then, there shalbe no neede, neither of foode, nor of procreation of children: Which thinges ſerue onely the vſe of this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal life. The reaſon of this is, becauſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely ſubſtances are not then worne or conſumed, there shall be no neede of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration by meate and drinke. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there shalbe no mortality, mariage shall not be then needefull by new pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, to preſerue and continue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and ſubſtances.</p>
            <p>Shining brightnes is alſo aſcribed by<note place="margin">Glorified bodies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with ſhining brightnes. <hi>Phi. 3.</hi>
               </note> the ſchoole men to glorified bodyes: wherof the Apoſtle ſpeaketh thus: <hi>Chriſt ſhall chaunge our vile bodies, and make them like to his glorious body. &amp;c.</hi> Some ſigne &amp;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20974:47"/> token hereof was giuen by Chriſt in hys tranſfiguration, when his face did shine like the ſun: &amp; the Euangeliſt ſaith: <hi>The</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 12. wiſe. 3. 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>iuſt ſhall ſhine as the ſunne in the ſight of God.</hi> Whereof the prophet Daniell alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mention. They aſcribe alſo to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified bodies nimblenes and agility: For<note place="margin">Glorified bodies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with agility.</note> the body and all the members shall be ſubiecte to the ſoule. And hereof it is written in the booke of wiſdome, of the ſainctes: <hi>That they ſhall be like ſparkes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">wiſed. 4.</note> 
               <hi>running amongſt the ſtubble:</hi> And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>We that ſhall be found alyue, and the dead who ſhall be rayſed, ſhalbe rapt to meete Chriſt in the ayre.</hi> The body of Chriſte walking vppon the watér was indued vvith this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gility, vvhiche he lent alſo for a tyme to Peter to do the ſame. The force or effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of this agility (as I ſayde before) is, that the ſoule shall haue abſolute domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ouer the body: in ſo much that the weight and burden of the flesh shall not in any wiſe hinder or lette the operation thereof. And alſo for that this qualitie apperteyneth to locall motion, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth<note place="margin">Vbiquiſtae.</note> many men to meruell, why the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biquaries are content to guyſe this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty in bodyes glorified, and yet will
<pb facs="tcp:20974:48"/> not graunt any place at all vnto them, as thoughe there coulde be a motion from place to place, without any place at all.</p>
            <p>The glorified bodyes alſo are impaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,<note place="margin">Glorified bodyes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſible.</note> that is to ſay, they shall not be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt or diminished with any paſſions, dolors, or diſeaſes: according as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle writeth, <hi>It is ſowen in corruption, it</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor 15. Paſſions of two ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> 
               <hi>riſeth againe in incorruption.</hi> And for that I haue ſayde, that the glorified bodies shal not be moleſted with paſsions, we muſt conſider that paſſions are of two ſortes. For ſome are noyſome and hurtefull to nature, afflicting and conſuming the body: as hunger, thirſt, ſickeneſſe, paine, and ſuch like. From theſe kindes of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, the ſaintes shall be deliuered. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, there are ſome other paſsions,<note place="margin">What kind of paſſions y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> glorified bodies ſhal haue.</note> which rather helpe and perfect nature, then hurt the ſame: Such are the notices of the ſenſes. The eye is not hurt with beholding of fayre colours, nor the eare with ſweete harmony and muſike: Nor yet is ſmelling hurt with good odours. Theſe and ſuche like good paſsions shall not be wanting to our bodyes glorified,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20974:48"/> vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vve shal reſt in our deſired cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey.<note place="margin">Glorified bodies thin and ſubtill.</note>
            </p>
            <p>They adde alſo ſubtilty to glorified bodyes, vvhiche is not ſo to be taken as though theſe bodies shoulde be turned into ſpirites &amp; become ayery, much like the winde pearcing all thinges: But this ſubtilty is rather to be referred to the exquiſite and perfect power of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Wherevnto may alſo be added af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, vvhich shall not be groſſe and earthly, moleſting the minde. In this ſenſe ſpake the Apoſtle: <hi>It is ſowen a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall body, but it riſeth agayne a ſpirituall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A naturall body, and a ſpirituall body. 1. Cor. 15.</note> In the vvhich vvordes he ment not that our bodyes shoulde be chaunged into ſpirites: But that they should come as neere the propertie of ſpirites as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly they might (in reſpect of their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices, and affections) reteyning ſtill their corporall nature and ſubſtance. Theſe notable properties are collected by the ſchoole men out of Gods vvord: many<note place="margin">Eſa. 6. 4. 1. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> others there be omitted, for it is truely ſayd, <hi>The eye hath not ſeene, the eare hath not harde, thoſe thinges which God hath prepared for thoſe that loue him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not vnmete to be obſerued in this
<pb facs="tcp:20974:49"/> place, that neither the holy ſcriptures,<note place="margin">Agaynſt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biquitie.</note> nor auncient Fathers, nor Scholaſticall writers, haue in any place aſcribed either to the bodies of Sainctes glorified, or to Chriſtes body <hi>vbiquitie,</hi> to be in no place, or in euery place. It is, &amp; that not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe wondred at, that ſome writers of our time doo ſo obſtinatly mainteine that opinion without any good ground at all. And it is to be noted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that many of the Scholemen: and amongſt others Thomas Aquinas, in conſideration that the bodies of bleſſed men ſhall come moſte neere vnto celeſtiall qualities: He inferreth vpon the ſame, that their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation ſhall be aboue all elementes in the ſupreme and high heauen.</p>
            <p>They diſpute alſo of the age of men in<note place="margin">Of what age bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies ſhal be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> their reſurrection, and their opinion is, that the ſame ſhal be freſhe, ſtrong, and luſtie: inforcing that of the Apoſtle to the prouing therof: <hi>vntill we growe in the vnitie of fayth, into the knowledge of the ſonne</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> 
               <hi>of God, into a perfect man, into the meaſure of the age of the fulneſſe of Chriſt.</hi> But by their patience the vvords of the Apoſtle tend to no ſuche ende: For he ſpeaketh not there of the reformation of bodies, but
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20974:49"/> of the renouatio of myndes, as the words going before, do moſt euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly declare. And yet I agree with them in the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of glorified bodyes: but in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort. For when god firſt created ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he made him no infant, no decrepit, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>med or vnperfit perſon. And ſeing the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a certen new kind of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, it muſt needes be lyke and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent vnto the firſt: As therfore all was very good, that is to ſaye, perfect in their kindes, vvhich god created: ſo shal mens bodies in the reſurrection in their kindes be abſolute and perfect.</p>
            <p>And theſe are the properties which the ſchoole men attribute to the bodyes of ſaintes in the reſurrection: Nowe if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will be inquiſitiue of the qualities &amp; conditions in the bodyes of vvicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when they shall ariſe to condemnation: Let him vnderſtande that they alſo shall haue immortality. But as for thoſe other<note place="margin">The quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked mens bodies in the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</note> ornaments of glorified bodies, they shal haue none at all: but rather shalbe diſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary deformities. For they shall haue no brightnes nor light, but as Chriſt hath taught, shalbe caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vtter darkeneſſe. Neither shall they be
<pb facs="tcp:20974:50"/> impaſsible, for they ſhal be afflicted with dolor &amp; paine without any intermiſsion. <hi>There ſhal be weeping and gnaſhing of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th. Their worme ſhal not dye, &amp; their fire ſhal not go out.</hi> They ſhall haue no nimblenes nor agilitie, <hi>for being bound ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; foote, they ſhal be caſt into helfire.</hi> They ſhal wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuch ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty &amp; purenes in affections, as I ſpake of before, becauſe they ſhall wepe &amp; wayle, &amp; be vexed with groſſe affections, &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement deſires: as we may ſee by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelical narration of Lazarus and the rich ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But in al theſe things that haue bin ſpoken hertofore in this matter, this is always to be had in memory, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding theſe varieties of qualities, yet the ſelfſame ſubſtance of our bodies ſhal not be altred. For the ſelfſame fleshe and body that we beare and carie about with vs nowe, shal be rayſed vp agayne at the laſte day. Hitherto Peter Martyr.</p>
            <p>The glorification of bleſſed men (ouer &amp; beſides thoſe things which I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the body) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in theſe things folowing. Firſt in iuſtice imputatiue in<note place="margin">Iuſtice im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tatiue.</note> chriſt: whereby thoſe ſhal pleaſe god euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly, that are iuſtified by fayth, and tranſlated into the heauenly Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20974:50"/> the prophet Daniel calleth that Iuſtice which is gotten by the death of Chriſte, <hi>ſempiternall.</hi> For this iuſtice vvhiche is ſo dearely bought by the ſonne of God, is not onely a merite for the which eternal life is giuen vnto men: but it is alſo their euerlaſting poſſeſsion, and the very wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<note place="margin">Math. 22.</note> garment, vvherewith men beeing clothed, may boldly ſitte downe at the banquet of their Lorde.</p>
            <p>It co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth alſo in notable &amp; excellent wiſdom, far paſsing that which euer any mundaine creature was indued withall. It hath alſo annexed vnto it, ſanctitie, puritie, &amp; a reſtitution of all powers, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel of the body, as of the ſoule. Theſe glorified natures ſhal haue a notable pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eminence ouer all mundaine creatures, whiche ſhall bee in the newe vvorlde, as ſome ſuppoſe, according to the good vvill and pleaſure of almightie God. For the Apoſtle Sainct Peter ſayth: <hi>Wee</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Eſai. 65.</note> 
               <hi>looke for a newe heauen and a newe earthe, according too hys promiſe, vvherein Iustice dwelleth.</hi> But touching the manner or order of theſe thynges, vvee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ught to referre them to Gods vvyll and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. He him ſelfe knoweth beſt howe he
<pb facs="tcp:20974:51"/> will doo them: and vve of the ſequeles &amp; conſequences, ſhal knowe the workes of god, which I the rather add bicauſe ſome may happily wonder at this doctrine.</p>
            <p>This immutation or reſtitution of man being thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plet &amp; finiſhed, &amp; the image of god being perfectly reſtored vnto ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into the kingdome of heauen.</note> he ſhal at the laſt be tranſlated into reall poſſeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly kingdom, which he had by faith &amp; hope only in this life, as Chriſt hath promiſed, that himſelf wil giue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in this forme: <hi>Come ye bleſſed children of my father, poſſeſſe the kingdome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for you from the beginning of the worlde.</hi> Mortal me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore ſhalbe remoued, not into any earthly, but into an heauenly Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, according to the words of chriſt ſpoken to the thiefe: <hi>This day thou ſhalt be</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 23.</note> 
               <hi>with me in paradiſe.</hi> Now in the poſſeſsion of this kingdom the godly ſhal haue end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ioy, wherwithal they ſhalbe crowned in ſteed of miſery, afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which they ſuffred for Chriſtes ſake in this mortal life: vvhich do ſo farre excel<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> thoſe miſeries, that there can be no iuſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon betwene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: which the ſame<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. 1. Pet. 1. and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5.</note> Apoſtle calleth the crown of Iuſtice: and S. Peter a crowne of glory vvhiche neuer
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20974:51"/> fadeth avvay. For firſt the Saincts ſhal ſee god, &amp; ſhal come to perfection in knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege: <hi>We ſee now in a glaſſe, &amp; in a dark ſpech,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.</note> 
               <hi>but then we ſhall ſee face to face.</hi> And what thing can there be more pleaſant or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon perſonally with our Redeemer, &amp; to heare him diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing heauenly things: vvhere is in deede the beſt Scholehouſe, &amp; notableſt Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of all ſapience &amp; vviſdome. We ſhal haue ſocietie &amp; familiaritie with the Angels, Archangels, &amp; al other heauenly povvers: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the Patriarks, Prophets &amp; Apoſtles: and with al thoſe that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of the world, haue bene ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers vnder the banner of Ieſus Chriſt. For as al damned perſons ſhalbe torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vvith the diuel &amp; his angels, in that lake that burneth with fire &amp; brimſtone: So shall the godly enioy endles felicitie in that moſt florishing kingdome, vvith the good &amp; iuſt angels eternally: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto<note place="margin">Perfect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience in men glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</note> shal be adioyned a vvilling obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence &amp; ſeruice of god, with al our harts, with al our minds, with al our willes, and with all our ſtrength. Then the which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience toward god our creator, redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer &amp; ſauiour, there ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be any thing
<pb facs="tcp:20974:52"/> more pleaſant &amp; delectable. There ſhall be no delight in carnal pleaſure, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of children, in mariages<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in worldly regimentes. All whiche thinges ſhall ceaſe: but we ſhal be buſied about things farre more excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, vvhich we ſee in a glymmis &amp; a farre of in this life, but ſhall knowe them perfectly in the life to come. And after al theſe things shal fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe a bleſſed life, and that without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, wherin shal be no dolor, ſickneſſe, or miſerie: nor yet shall death haue any povver there, according to the promiſe of our fauiour Chriſt, <hi>He that beleeueth in</hi>
               <note place="margin">John. 3.</note> 
               <hi>me ſhall haue eternall life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This their glorificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will be more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant<note place="margin">The tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of hell.</note> vnto vs now and, then alſo, if we on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther ſide co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the woe &amp; miſery which damned perſons ſhall abide eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally: for vnto the great ioyes of the godly, there are correſpondent ſo many tormentes of the vngodly. And fyrſte, thoſe miſerable men ſhall want the ſight or viſion of God: the want of which is called of late Diuines, <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>na damni, payne</hi>
               <note place="margin">The payne of loſſe.</note> 
               <hi>of loſse:</hi> Whiche is ſo greeuous a thing by the opinion of Chryſoſtome, and S. Auguſtine, that it were better to be in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20974:52"/> hell enioying that viſion, then to be in any place vvithout it. Vnto the whiche <hi>payne of loſſe,</hi> there is added intolerable torments of fyre &amp; brimſtone: and many other infinit agonies &amp; vexations, which the Diuines call <hi>Penam ſenſus, the payne of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Payne of ſence.</note> 
               <hi>ſence,</hi> or feling. The which two paynes are neuer without deſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate houling, wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, &amp; gnashing of teeth. What should I here ſpeake of the ſun dry and diuers kinds of torments, vvherwithall damned perſons vexe one another in hell: which are ſo vgglie &amp; horrible that we tremble and quake, when we do but once thinke vpon them: and are ſo muche more gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, becauſe all releefe and ende ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, are vtterly diſpayred and diſtruſted. And the ſame are not a litle augmented, when damned men shall caſte vp their eyes into heauen, and beholde thoſe<note place="margin">Sap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4,</note> vvhom they had in this worlde in deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: novve on the contrarie parte to reſt in peace, and to reigne in all glory, honor, and bleſſedneſſe.</p>
            <p>There are two queſtions vſually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> eq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie or ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitie of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyes in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life.</note> touching the ſtate of glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: firſt, whether the glory of the Elect be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to all, without any differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of
<pb facs="tcp:20974:53"/> mens accions or vocations in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life: or vvhether there be any diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie at all. Secondly, whether in the ſtate of glorification, men shall knowe ſuch as were their acquaintance &amp; frends in this life. Of the vvhich two queſtions, albeit not impartinent to this diſcourſe, I vvill write nothing at this time: both becauſe the diſcuſsing of theſe queſtions (in my iudgement) breede rather pleaſure then profit: &amp; alſo bicauſe the ſame are hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led<note place="margin">Rog. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeus ex Pe. Mart. in 1. Cor. 14. The ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans ſalue</note> learnedly in our English tong, by two of our countrey men, <hi>M. Allie,</hi> and <hi>M. Beacon,</hi> (albeit one of them borowed his tractation of this matter almoſt verba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim out of <hi>P. Martyr</hi>) vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore I remitte the Reader deſitous to knovve further of this matter. I thinke it rather<note place="margin">Drigans &amp; the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s error touching y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſaluation of all men.</note> expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to admonish my reader in this part, of the hereſie of the <hi>Chiliaſtes,</hi> vvho ſuppoſed, that both al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; diuels shuld be ſaued at the laſt day. Of the vvhich o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion vvas Origen: who alſo helde that the benefite of Chriſt should extende it ſelfe as largely as the offence of Adam. But there is playne &amp; euident mention made in the holy ſcripture of the paynes of damned men. <hi>Their worme ſhall neuer
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20974:53"/> dye.</hi> Nether is it expreſſed in the ſcripture that Chriſtes binefite shuld be exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded as ample as the fall of Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And albeit ſome mainteining that propoſition to helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, do affirme that Chriſtes benefit extendeth it ſelfe to ſo many in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, in reſpect that by his meanes al men are par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>takers of the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: vnto this it may be inferred, that as the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to the godly, ſo is it a punishment to the vngodly. For the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the wicked is vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> partly an execution of gods ſeueritie and wrath. And if the lord pronounced of Iudas, <hi>that it had bin better for him neuer to haue bin borne:</hi> why may not<note place="margin">It were better for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wicked ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to riſe a gayne.</note> the ſame be ſpoken of the wicked, <hi>It were better for them not to riſe agayne.</hi> Moreouer albeit they ſeme to haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſome refuge in reſpect of the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, bicauſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes benefit is ſpred to as many in number as Adams tranſgreſsion, what would they anſwer, if they ſhuld be vrged with an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of Adams offence, &amp; Chriſtes iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: Will they ſay that all haue bin ſo iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in Chriſte, as they haue ſinned in Adam? Surely to this they can not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwere. For not ſo many by much ſhal be iuſtified by Chriſte, as shall be damned in
<pb facs="tcp:20974:54"/> Adam. And this is the minde of <hi>P. Martyr</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pe. Mar. in. 1. Cor. 15.</note> in this matter: and the Apoſtle him ſelfe ſeemeth to reſtrayne Chriſtes benefits, to thoſe that haue receiued the abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of grace, &amp; gyft of righteouſnes. <hi>For if by the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> 
               <hi>ſinne of one, death raigned by the meanes of one: much more they whiche receiue abundaunce of grace, &amp; the gift of righteouſnes, ſhall reigne in lyfe, by the meanes of one, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And albeit I yeeld willingly to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer<note place="margin">The ſtate of man glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> firſte ſtate of man after his creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> opinion touching the extending of Chriſtes benefites to the fewer nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber: yet it is to be added, that the effects of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites &amp; gifts of chriſt are more ample &amp; notable to that number, which are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the ſame in the ſtate of glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The dignitie of the image of god af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his creation, was no doubt notable &amp; excellent, &amp; did brightly shew foorth the loue of the creator toward the creature: but that image of god which shalbe reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after the reſurrection, to al thoſe that beleue in Chriſt, shal be much more excel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lent. For we shal be colored and clenſed with the precious blood of Chriſt. And this reſtitution shal be perpetuall &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, wheras in the firſt ſtate of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was changeable, &amp; indured for a short time. And as the heauenly life vvyth
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20974:54"/> Chriſt dothe farre excell the earthly lyfe with Adam befere his fall: euen ſo no doubt the image of god perfectly reſtored by Chriſt in glorification, shal much excel the firſt donatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but bicauſe the curious ſifting of theſe matters paſſe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of mans capacitie, and ſmal is the ſmacke that we haue of theſe things, vvhiles our foules are clogged with earthly veſſels: let vs beſech Chriſt to haſten his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, that we may take poſſeſsion of that heauenly heritage, where we shal beholde all thoſe things, euen with theſe eyes of ours, and enioy the ſame in our bodies and ſoules.</p>
            <p>This excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reſtitution of the faythful,<note place="margin">Glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the worke and gift of Chriſt.</note> may not be aſcribed to their owne works (albeit god in his mercy promiſeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward &amp; crown the ſame) but onely to the mercy of God in his ſonne Chriſt. For as the reſurrection from the dead, is neither the work of man, nor of angels, but of god alone: euen ſo al thoſe things vvhich ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteine to mans eternall glorification, proceede only of the power &amp; goodnes of god, in exhibiting his ſonne to finish this vvorke. As the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>We are recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> 
               <hi>to god by the death of his ſonne.</hi> Agayne, <hi>Receyuing abundance of grace and iuſtice: they
<pb facs="tcp:20974:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhall reigne in life by one man, Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And alſo, <hi>He roſe agayne for our iuſtification.</hi> And<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> hereof it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe that our ſauiour Chriſt is ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times in the ſcripture called our life; <hi>I am the way, the truth, and the life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 14. 10 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heworke of redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion is only Chriſtes.</note> And, <hi>I came that they mighte haue life.</hi> Euen ſo is the donation of eternall life aſcribed vnto him: And the reaſon is, becauſe he is our Mediator &amp; Redemer. For albeit the<note place="margin">Joh. 14.</note> father and the ſonne are one, yet will the father be knowen in his ſonne only: and it is the ſonne only that demeriteth &amp; ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the holy ghoſt into the harts of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers.<note place="margin">Jo. 16. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The vvordes of Athanaſius are worthy the obſeruation in this matter: <hi>It</hi>
               <note place="margin">Athanaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> 
               <hi>was requiſite that the ſonne ſhould aſſume mans nature, that by meanes of the eſſentiall Image of god, man being the create image, might be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> Wherof Origen alſo writeth excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently:<note place="margin">Origines.</note> 
               <hi>Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brought the maligne image throgh ſinne, therfore Christ came in the likenes of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to reforme vs according to his image.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Novv that vvee all may be partakers of this glorification, it behoueth vs to begin new obedience in this life, which is accep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table to god, through Chriſt: and as the Apoſtle doth exhort vs: <hi>Let vs put on the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> 
               <hi>new man, which after God is formed in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20974:55"/> and holynes of truth.</hi> Let vs alvvayes haue in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, that this life of ours is nothing els but a pilgrimage, through the vvhich vvee muſt trauell into eternall life. Let vs forget thoſe things that are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde our backes, and deſire thoſe things that are before our faces: Let vs ame to the marke, euen to the garland of eternal life, through Ieſus Chriſt: Let vs be certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded (as the truth is in dede) that there can be no greater plague, then to be ſeparate from God by ſinne: &amp; in place of eternal ioy, to abide eternal miſery, &amp; for ſwete life, to receiue bitter death. Let the conſideration of Gods image imparted vnto mankinde, moue vs to haue alvvayes in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance gods great loue tovvarde vs, &amp; our dutie to him againe: Wherof S.<note place="margin">Auguſt. libe. de ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut. doc. cap. 3.</note> Auguſtine writeth excellently after this maner: <hi>Vnderſtand (O man) by thy honor in thy first eſtate, how much thou are bound to thy creator: which digniti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aunced thee vnto, that thou ſhould ſo much the more loue him as he</hi>
               <note place="margin">The effect and fruite which ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulde ſpring by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of theſe thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>hath pref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rred thee in honor before all mundaine creatures. For by the counſayle of the holy trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, thou waſt not onely excellently created: but created after the ſimilitude &amp; image of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, which was not collated to any other creature
<pb facs="tcp:20974:56"/> but to man only.</hi> By this and ſuch like conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, it shal come to paſſe, by the aide of Gods grace, that we shal defie &amp; treade down earthly things, &amp; couet celeſtial &amp; heauenly things: We shal ſay with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>I deſire to be loſed, &amp; to be with Christ:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phi. 1.</note> So shal <hi>we dye bleſſedly, and reſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all labors:</hi>
               <note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u. 14. Phi. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſo ſhall we ariſe agayne to immortalitie, and our bodies ſhal be conformed vnto the body of chriſt.</hi> And ſo we shal haue perfect felicitie, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ioyned to god the perfect goodnes, in perfect loue: and the image of God, after the which we be firſt created, shalbe more perfectly abſolued in vs. In the whiche I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage there shal ſhine perfect iuſtice, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect holynes, perfect libertie, perfect vviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, perfect clearnes &amp; glory, wherof the Prophet ſpeaketh, ſaying: <hi>I ſhal be ſatiſfied, when I ſhall awake according to thy ſimilitude.</hi> Whervnto Salomon alſo alludeth, ſaying, <hi>The eye is not ſatiſfied with ſeeing, neither is the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclſi. 1.</note> 
               <hi>eare filled with hearing.</hi> In whiche ſentence<note place="margin">Godly men are ſatiſfied onely in the fruition of heauenly thinges.</note> the Wiſeman ſignifieth, that nothing can ſuffiſe man, before he come to god, &amp; reſt in him. For there is in man ſuch a deſire of diuine things, that nothing can ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent him, but that which is the chiefeſt: which when he obteineth, then he reſteth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20974:56"/> in the ſame as in the cheefe felicitie. And therfore his perfit eſtate muſt nedes be in eternal bleſſednes which we begin here in this life, &amp; abſolue perfectly in the life to come: vvherof Proſper ſpeaketh: <hi>The life to come, is beleeued to be bleſſed ſempiternally, &amp; ſempiternally bleſſed where there is perfect loue, &amp; no feare.</hi> The ſtate of this bleſſednes was offred to <hi>S.</hi> Iohn in a viſion: <hi>He ſawe the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 21.</note> 
               <hi>holy citie Ieruſalem prepared like a ſpouſe for her huſbande Christ: in the which there was neither mourning, neither clamor, nor death: but ioye, peace, quietnes, &amp; euerlaſting life. Whoſe walles</hi>
               <note place="margin">A certen deſcription of the ioyes of heauen out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture</note> 
               <hi>were of precious ſtone, And the citie was pure golde like vnto cleare glaſſe: and the foundations of the wall of the citie were garniſhed with all maner of precious ſtones. The twelue gates were twelue pearles, euery gate was of one pearle, and the ſtreete of the citie was pure gold, as it were ſhining glaſſe. And I ſawe no temple therein, for the Lord god almightie, &amp; the Lambe, are the temple of it. And the Citie had no neede of the ſunne, neither of the moone, to lighten it, for the glory of God, &amp; the lambe is the light of it. And the nacions of them which are ſaued, ſhal walke in the light of it: and the kings of the earth do bring their glorie and honor vnto it. And the gates of it ſhal not be ſhut at all by day: for there
<pb facs="tcp:20974:57"/> ſhall be no night. And they ſhall bring the glory and honor of the gentiles vnto it. And there ſhall in no wiſe enter into it any vncleane thing, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what ſoeuer worketh abhomination, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth lyes: but they onely which are vvritten in the lambes booke of life.</hi> The image of true felicitie which we couet &amp; deſire, is after a ſort repreſented vnto vs in this deſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which albeit it doth not, nor can not liuely &amp; perfectly expreſſe the ſame: yet it is propoſed both to ſtirre vs vp to an earneſt deſire thereof, and to kindle in vs an ardent loue of pietie and all other heauenly vertues: vntill vve haue runne out our race in this life, &amp; do come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the goale or garland of promiſed feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, vvhich is ſo incomprehenſible to all humaine ſpeeche, penne, and cogitation, that the Apoſtle in the declaration ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, findeth in him ſelfe ſome defecte and vvante: and therefore repeteth oute of the Prophet, <hi>The eye hath not ſeene, the eare</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 64. 1. Cor. 2.</note> 
               <hi>hath not heard, neither hath the hart of man conceyued thoſe Ioyes, vvhiche God hath prepared for thoſe that loue him.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20974:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
